<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Isabel Costa</title>
	<subtitle></subtitle>
	<link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//"/>
	
	<updated>2017-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
	
	<id>https://isabelcosta.github.io/</id>
	<author>
  <name>Isabel Costa</name>
  <email>isabel.monteiro.costa@gmail.com</email>
	</author>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>2020 Review</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/2020-review/"/>
    <updated>2021-02-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/2020-review/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p>2020 was a very year particular year! Many things happened... 😳 I want to highlight some of the interesting achievements at a professional level.</p>
<p>I never get these reviews done at the end of year... Here’s a summary of some achievements (not in order):</p>
<ul>
<li>Made <a href="https://youtu.be/-EFVDjDdeXw?t=6766">my first conference talk in Portuguese</a>! This was at DevFest Portugal 🇵🇹 I was super happy, it was intimidating, as I am mostly used to do talks in English, so trying to speak about open source in Portuguese without speaking with too many &quot;english&quot; terms, was a challenge. I loved it, and after that, I did 2 more in Portuguese, and it's such a pleasure 🤗</li>
<li>Wrote <a href="/posts/ficheiros-base-num-projeto-open-source/">my first post in Portuguese</a>, about Open Source. It was a challenge just like the first Portuguese talk, but I really wanted to do it.</li>
<li>Participated in a podcast for the first time! This <a href="https://anchor.fm/codingblackfemales/episodes/Isabel-Costa---Contributing-to-Open-Source-eiavh6">was with Coding Black Females podcast</a>. It was a super interesting experience that I especially loved because of the community it was for!</li>
<li>Co-organized multiple meetups as part of my volunteer work as Community Leader at AnitaB.org London community. In particular, a meetup about public speaking was such an intense experience. I have GREAT respect for community organizers, not just for the meetups, but also all the logistics involved in keeping a community alive and engaged.</li>
<li>Had <a href="https://youtu.be/KGG3PXYwKIE?t=1491">first lightning talk and it was not related to open source</a>! This is super important because I want to be able to articulate my non open source related knowledge and thoughts. With this, I was able to get out of my comfort zone, of talking about open source. I talked about a topic I am super interested in, documentation and transparency at work. This was at Ladies of Code London, an awesome community, I am super happy to be a part of 🤗</li>
<li>I was made redundant and recovered from it. This was one of the toughest things that I experienced this year. I could never imagine it happening until it did. I am super grateful to be with my family at that time in Portugal and to have friends that supported me throughout this time. I went through the job hunting process, which can be extremely emotional and energy draining, and soon enough found another job 🙏🏾</li>
<li>Became admin for <a href="https://github.com/anitab-org">AnitaB.org Open Source</a>! So this year, I got to help the community at a more broad level, other than maintaining projects (which I also did) and I loved it. I learned a lot from doing admin work with my co-admins.</li>
<li>As part of this, I also participated on GSoC as an admin on AnitaB.org Open Source, 2 years after participating on GSoC as a student. It was basically a full circle of these google open source programs, such an interesting and rewarding experience.</li>
<li>Mentored at <a href="https://blackcodher.com/">Black Codher</a> bootcamp - 6-month Coding Bootcamp programme in the UK for black women. This was such an impactful and meaningful experience for me for the cause it stands for. I got to be a mentor I wanted to have in my early years, but to a newcomer to the tech industry. I learned a lot from this experience and met incredible people who care about the cause and are super knowledgeable. I even learned a little of React to help my mentee 😅</li>
</ul>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>How to change last commit message</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/how-to-change-last-commit-message/"/>
    <updated>2020-11-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/how-to-change-last-commit-message/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p>Often when making changes to code, I commit them and then have to change to commit I just made, either because I think the commit message could be better or I had to make a last-minute change to the code I wish to include in the commit.</p>
<h3>Change last commit message</h3>
<p>So consider I committed changes with the following command (<code>-m</code> to write one line commit message):</p>
<pre><code>git commit -m &quot;fix: big feature X&quot;
</code></pre>
<p>Here’s how I fix the commit, using the <code>--amend</code> option.</p>
<pre><code>git commit --amend -m &quot;fix: small feature X&quot;
</code></pre>
<p>In case I want to add additional code to the commit, I run <code>git add &lt;file&gt;</code> before running <code>git commit --amend</code>.</p>
<h3>Verify new commit message</h3>
<p>To check that it worked and I fixed the right commit I check the latest commit with:</p>
<pre><code>git log --oneline
</code></pre>
<p>I use <code>--oneline</code> because I just want to see the commit messages, instead of also seeing the name and email of the author of the commit. You’ll an output similar to this, where you can see the last commit has the correct message:</p>
<pre><code>1792519 (HEAD -&gt; master, origin/master, origin/HEAD) fix: small feature X
701aa33  docs: add instructions to README
(END)
</code></pre>
<p>In my environment, this will open vim, which I close by typing <code>:q</code>.</p>
<h3>Fix pushed commit</h3>
<p>In case I already pushed to the remote repository the commit I want to fix, I force the push to remote to update the commit. Preferably, you are working on a feature specific branch, which does not affect the main one (in case this messes the git history for some reason). So this is what I would run, where <code>&lt;branch&gt;</code> is the branch you are working on (e.g.: <code>master</code>).</p>
<pre><code>git push -f origin &lt;branch&gt;
</code></pre>
<hr>
<p>Hope this helps you fix the last commit message.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Ficheiros base num projeto Open Source</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/ficheiros-base-num-projeto-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2020-11-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/ficheiros-base-num-projeto-open-source/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p>Um projecto Open Source costuma ter uma base de ficheiros, que permite colaboradores perceber como devem interagir com o projecto e quais as expectativas de quem mantém o projecto (maintainer). Estes são os ficheiros base que projetos open source costumam ter.</p>
<h2>Licença</h2>
<p>A Licença de um projeto open source é importante para os colaboradores saberem em que condições podem usar o projeto. No que diz respeito ao tipo de licença que se deve escolher, isso depende do projeto. Eu sei que há umas licenças mais permissivas que outras. Há licenças que permite a modificação e reutilização, etc, desde que o crédito seja devidamente atribuído aos criadores do projeto.</p>
<p>Este ficheiro costuma estar na raiz do projeto. E normalmente tem o seguinte nome: <code>LICENSE.md</code> ou <code>LICENSE.txt</code>.</p>
<p>Há um website que explica diferentes tipos de licenças - <a href="https://choosealicense.com/">choosealicense.com</a>. Aqui podes tentar perceber qual o que se adequa melhor ao teu projeto open source.</p>
<h2>Código de conduta</h2>
<p>É muito importante ter um código de conduta num projeto open source. Isto permite aos colaboradores saberem que tipo de conduta é a adequada e a que não é aceitável na comunidade a volta de um projeto de modo a manter o conjunto de interações, na comunidade, segura e amigável para todos. Este ficheiro, também deve conter informações de como reportar violações deste código de conduta por parte de membros da comunidade, para que o ou a maintainer possa tomar as devidas ações.</p>
<p>Se quiseres saber de exemplos de código de conduta, podes encontrar um bom exemplo, já adotado por vários projetos, em <a href="https://www.contributor-covenant.org/">www.contributor-covenant.org</a>. Este modelo de código de conduta tem traduções em várias linguas, incluindo <a href="https://www.contributor-covenant.org/pt/version/1/4/code-of-conduct/">versão em português</a>.</p>
<h2>README.md</h2>
<p>O <code>README</code> é o ponto de partida de um colaborador num projeto Open Source. É neste ficheiro que se espera aprender mais sobre o projeto, como a sua missão e descrição, instruções para ter o projeto a funcionar, etc... Por isso é super importante que haja informação relevante para colaboradores sobre o projeto e links para o resto da documentação. O formato e o conteúdo deste ficheiro pode variar de projeto para projeto, o que interessa é que novos potenciais colaboradores, encontrem informação necessária para explorar mais sobre o projeto. Há projetos em que o <code>README</code> representa a maior parte do projeto em si, por exemplo se o repositório for apenas conteúdo informativo como awesome lists (ex.: <a href="https://github.com/vinta/awesome-python">vinta/awesome-python</a> no GitHub). Este ficheiro, encontra-se na raiz do projeto. Por vezes, podem haver outros tipos de <code>README</code> presentes em pastas do repositório, que podem explicar em detalhe informações relevantes sobre o conteúdo específico da pasta.</p>
<h2>Guia de contribuição</h2>
<p>O guia de contribuição, <code>CONTRIBUTING.md</code>, ajuda colaboradores a perceber o tipo de e os passos para uma contribuição bem sucedida. Os passos de contribuição para um projeto podem diferir de projeto para projeto. Na comunidade onde estou, <a href="https://github.com/anitab-org">AnitaB.org Open Source</a>, nós pedimos aos colaboradores para criar uma <em>issue</em> antes de submeter uma pull request (caso a issue não exista). Isto pode ser útil para nós que por vezes temos muitas contribuições, e podemos assim validar rapidamente <em>Pull Requests</em> que são spam ou inválidas, e fechá-las. No entanto, já contribui para projetos, como na <a href="/posts/my-first-open-source-contribution">minha primeira contribuição para Open Source</a>, no qual podia simplesmente criar PRs com as minhas sugestões de melhoria do projeto, sem necessidade de criar uma issue antes. Como <em>maintainer</em>, é neste ficheiro que se deve definir as expectativas que temos para com e dos colaboradores.</p>
<p>Dependendo do projeto, podes encontrar este ficheiro na raiz do projeto, ou em pastas específicas (exemplos de pastas são <code>.github</code> no GitHub, <code>.gitlab</code> no GitLab ou docs).</p>
<h2>Modelos de Issue e PRs</h2>
<p>Modelos de <em>issues</em> e de <em>Pull Requests</em> (PRs) pode ser útil para fazer com que haja consistência nas descrições das mesmas. Estes ficheiros, servem de exemplo e são usados no ato de criação das mesmas. No GitHub e no GitLab podes tê-las numas pastas especificas <code>.github</code> ou <code>.gitlab</code>, respectivamente, para as issues e PRs serem automaticamente preenchidas com os modelos, que depois os colaboradores apenas terão de editar. Como <em>maintainer</em>, isto será útil para que colaboradores prestem especial atenção às expectativas dos maintainers para contribuições. Nestes modelos podes ter uma lista de pré-requisitos de uma contribuição, que pode facilitar o trabalho de triagem das <em>issues</em> e PRs (exemplo: link para documentação regras de estilo de código, secção para descrever testes manuais feitos para uma nova funcionalidade adicionada, seção para incluir imagens tiradas das modificações a interface de utilizador como ecrã da aplicação, etc...).</p>
<p>Se quiseres um exemplo de modelos de issues, um dos projectos que mantenho tem <a href="https://github.com/anitab-org/mentorship-backend/tree/develop/.github/ISSUE_TEMPLATE">diferentes tipos de modelos para issues</a> e exemplo de <a href="https://github.com/anitab-org/mentorship-backend/blob/develop/.github/PULL_REQUEST_TEMPLATE.md">modelo de descrição de PRs</a>. Também podes encontrar diferentes modelos neste repositorio - <a href="https://github.com/devspace/awesome-github-templates">devspace/awesome-github-templates</a>.</p>
<h2>Descrição e Tópicos</h2>
<p>Descrição e Tópicos não são representados em forma de ficheiros, mas são igualmente importantes para a base de um projeto open source. Estes no GitHub, como dois campos que podes preencher sobre um repositório. Ambos os campos são das primeiras informações que um colaborador pode ver sobre o projeto. Este aparece quando o projeto é listado, sem precisarmos de estar na página do repositório. Por isso uma boa descrição e tópicos relevantes podem ser a diferença entre um colaborador decidir ver mais sobre o projeto ou não. Isto também se aplica a tópicos.
Como <em>developer</em> de uma certa tech stack, eu posso pesquisar projectos que usam uma <em>tech stack</em> específica. Mesmo não sendo developer, posso querer encontrar projetos de impacto social, e pesquisar esse tópico específico. Isto ajuda a um colaborador ter uma ideia de um projeto, antes de ir a página do projeto e também perceber se é algo para o qual quer contribuir.</p>
<hr>
<p>Espero que isto te ajude se estiveres a começar um projeto ou a melhorá-lo para conseguires ter um projeto mais atrativo para novos colaboradores.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>My first mentorship experience</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/my-first-mentorship-experience/"/>
    <updated>2020-09-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/my-first-mentorship-experience/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p>I got into university, <a href="https://tecnico.ulisboa.pt/">Instituto Superior Tecnico</a> in TagusPark, to pursue Communications Networks degree (now called Telecommunications and Informatics Engineering) without knowing anything about programming. The first programming course I had was the Programming Foundations course, in which in the first classes I found myself a bit lost. In this course, we were taught how to code through Python. So this was the first programming language I learned!</p>
<p>In one of the programming labs, I did an exercise which I thought I performed poorly. I was failing to understand basic concepts, such as how and when to use a “while” loop.</p>
<p>After that class where I felt very frustrated and sad by not getting some basic concepts, one of the first-year mentors, from <a href="https://nape.tecnico.ulisboa.pt/">NAPE (Student Support Unit)</a>, found me and asked how I was getting with the first classes. I was completely honest and explained I was feeling lost and did not understand the exercise I just had completed in the class board. She was super kind and offered to meet with me the next Friday at 6 pm (same week) to help me get unstuck in my learnings.</p>
<p>That Friday, she set down with me in a classroom that only had some students studying on their own, and explained to me some basic programming concepts such as while loops and other operations. In that meet things just clicked in my head! After this, I got unblocked and understood that it's all about logic. Since then I started doing much better and picking up concepts so much easier!</p>
<p>From this little story and all my experience ever since getting into this tech industry, I feel that sometimes people just need a little push to unlock their potential.</p>
<p>I’m glad that there are programs such as NAPE, a student support unit at Instituto Superior Técnico, which helped me get in touch with other more advanced students who could encourage and support me as a first-year student.</p>
<p>The second year of college, a professor involved with the mentoring and tutoring program, invited me and other students to become mentors. I decided to accept it and contribute to the mentors' mission, to help newcomers to college adjust to academic life. Through this experience, I met mentees and mentors who became friends and got to give back to the same program that helped me so much as a newcomer coming from another city.</p>
<p>I feel that mentoring is such an important thing to have in life. Having people vouching for you, that want you to succeed and support you in the learning journey can make a great impact on your life and career.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>My First Open Source Contribution</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/my-first-open-source-contribution/"/>
    <updated>2020-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/my-first-open-source-contribution/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <!-- ![first contribution illustrative image](/images/my-first-contribution-promo.png) -->
<p>For a long time, I thought about contributing to Open Source, but I felt I did not know where to start. As a software engineer, I wanted to learn and build a portfolio of work through contributing to Open Source.</p>
<p>Back in December 2017, I got the word of <a href="https://24pullrequests.com/">24 Pull Requests</a>, an initiative with a Christmas feel to it, where you can contribute to open source projects during the month of December.</p>
<p><img src="/images/24-pull-requests.png" alt="24 Pull Requests website image)"></p>
<p>When I found about this, I decided to look into it and see if I could contribute. To start I thought about contributing with a “low hanging fruit” sort of issue. Even though my main interest was in coding, I wanted to start with the documentation type of contribution. So I looked into projects made of markdown files and found <a href="https://github.com/fvcproductions/hire-me/pull/9">fvcproductions/hire-me</a> which is about providing resources and advice for people looking for jobs, such as interview tips, job boards, and other types of resources.</p>
<p>So after looking into this project I noticed that there was a job board that I knew that was not there so I saw an opportunity to contribute.</p>
<p>Next, I read the <a href="https://github.com/fvcproductions/hire-me#contributing">contribution guidelines which were very simple</a>. The steps provided in this project guidelines were: 1. fork repository; 2. read contribution guidelines; 3. add my name to the credits section; 4. Open Pull Request; 5. Get pull request approved 🎉</p>
<p>So after I forked the repository, I added my changes and my name to the credits in the README, and submitted a Pull Request. Here’s <a href="https://github.com/fvcproductions/hire-me/pull/9">my pull request #9</a>!</p>
<p>Some days after the maintainer of the repository merged my PR and thanked me for my contribution! I was so happy that I finally managed to do my first open source contribution after so much time delaying it. After this moment, I knew the basics of an open source workflow and I could apply to other contributions.</p>
<p>Have you ever contributed to Open Source? If not, I hope this inspires you to get started :)</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>🎧 Podcasts I listen to</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/podcasts-i-enjoy/"/>
    <updated>2020-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/podcasts-i-enjoy/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p>I usually listen to podcasts on Spotify. These are some of the podcasts I follow and listen to, more on the tech industry spectrum, whether discussing latest trends in tech industry or experiences in it.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.techishpod.com/">Techish podcast</a></li>
<li><a href="https://gitcutepodcast.com/">Git Cute podcast</a></li>
<li><a href="https://codingblackfemales.com/podcast">Coding Black Females podcast</a></li>
<li><a href="https://ladybug.dev">Ladybug podcast</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.codenewbie.org/podcast">CodeNewbie podcast</a></li>
<li><a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/ca/podcast/sauce-control/id1527090126">Sauce Control</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.hanselminutes.com/">Hanselminutes podcast</a></li>
<li><a href="https://softskills.audio/">Soft Skills engineering</a></li>
<li><a href="https://saharmandi.com/podcast/">Speak Up and Lead with Sahar Mandi</a></li>
<li><a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/tech-unlocked/id1488455514">Tech Unlocke‪d‬</a></li>
</ul>
<p><em>This post might be update from time to time, either I'll add new podcasts or add description to the podcasts I love.</em></p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Deploying Mentorship Backend flask app on Heroku</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/deploy-ms-to-heroku/"/>
    <updated>2020-06-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/deploy-ms-to-heroku/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/deploy-ms-heroku-cover.png" alt=""></p>
<p>At <a href="https://github.com/anitab-org">AnitaB.org Open Source</a> we have a project called Mentorship System, which I started during <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code</a> 2018. This project is composed of several repositories: <a href="https://github.com/anitab-org/mentorship-flutter">flutter</a>, <a href="https://github.com/anitab-org/mentorship-android">android</a>, <a href="https://github.com/anitab-org/mentorship-ios">ios</a>, and a <a href="https://github.com/anitab-org/mentorship-backend">backend</a> written in Python (Flask).</p>
<p>I want to describe how I deployed the backend REST API project on <a href="https://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a>, using its <a href="https://www.heroku.com/pricing">free tier</a>.</p>
<h3>Setup project to be deployable on Heroku ⚒️</h3>
<p>So <a href="https://github.com/anitab-org/mentorship-backend">anitab-org/mentorship-backend</a> already could be run locally using simply <code>python run.py</code> command on a terminal and having the environment variables set.</p>
<p>However, I had to create a specific file and indicate the way I wanted to run the backend app on Heroku.</p>
<p>So to enable the project as it is to deploy on Heroku with a single click, just by connecting it with GitHub, I had to create a new file on the project called <code>Procfile</code> with this line, where <code>application</code> refers to the object that holds the flask app.</p>
<pre><code>web: gunicorn run:application
</code></pre>
<p>I created this pull request (PR) <a href="https://github.com/anitab-org/mentorship-backend/pull/640">#640 on anitab-org/mentorship-backend</a> to add the changes mentioned above. With these changes, anyone that forks the project on GitHub can follow the same procedure as I did and deploy the project on Heroku.</p>
<h3>Deploy on Heroku 🚀</h3>
<p>Now that the project has everything that it needs to run on Heroku, let's create the configuration. In my personal account dashboard, I started by creating the app.</p>
<p><img src="/images/deploy-ms-heroku-2.png" alt="I clicked the “Create new app” option on my Dashboard"></p>
<p>I gave it the name of the app, that will compose the Heroku app URL. In my case to get <a href="https://mentorship-backend-temp.herokuapp.com/">mentorship-backend-temp.herokuapp.com</a> I named the app <code>mentorship-backend-temp</code> . I also had to select a region between United States and Europe.</p>
<p><img src="/images/deploy-ms-heroku-3.png" alt="“Create New App” view on Heroku"></p>
<p>Then I clicked the <strong>“Connect with GitHub” option in the “Deployment method” section</strong> from the Deploy tab (which I was redirected to) and selected a repository on the <strong>“Connect to GitHub” section</strong>, such as my mentorship-backend fork repository. Because I am one of the admins of the <a href="https://github.com/anitab-org">anitab-org on GitHub</a>, I ended up selecting is from the organization, instead of from my account.</p>
<p><img src="/images/deploy-ms-heroku-4.png" alt="Connecting to GitHub on Heroku"></p>
<p>At this point, with the app configured on Heroku and connected to GitHub, we are able to see the current deployments of the app on both platforms.</p>
<p><img src="/images/deploy-ms-heroku-5.png" alt="I set the Deployment method to GitHub"></p>
<p><img src="/images/deploy-ms-heroku-6.png" alt="Deployment link is available at {repository}/deployments on GitHub"></p>
<p>Next, I had to <strong>create the</strong> <a href="https://github.com/anitab-org/mentorship-backend/blob/develop/docs/environment-variables.md"><strong>environment variables</strong></a> that the project needs to run properly and also connect with a remote database. This section is available <strong>in the “Settings” tab</strong> of the app view on Heroku.</p>
<p><img src="/images/deploy-ms-heroku-7.png" alt="Environment Variables Configuration section on Heroku"></p>
<p>Then I made sure to <strong>deploy this app from the “Deploy” tab</strong>. As a result of this action, we have now the project deployed at:</p>
<p>→ <a href="https://mentorship-backend-temp.herokuapp.com/">https://mentorship-backend-temp.herokuapp.com/</a></p>
<p>In the end, I also <strong>enabled the Automatic Deploys</strong> feature. For that, I went to the page of the application on Heroku and went to the Deploy tab, and then enabled it. I could also enable Manual Deploy, which I used before, but since we are now paying close attention to what gets merged, I was confident in enabling it.</p>
<p><img src="/images/deploy-ms-heroku-8.png" alt="Automatic Deploys section on Deploy tab in Heroku app view"></p>
<p>Now that the app is deployed, I can access the logs of this server, and debug if anyone experiences a bug specific to this running instance of the app. Although we can only see the most recent logs, it still comes in handy.</p>
<p><img src="/images/deploy-ms-heroku-9.png" alt="View logs of mentorship app on Heroku"></p>
<h3>Benefits for the community 👐🏾</h3>
<p><img src="/images/deploy-ms-heroku-10.png" alt="medium dark skin woman technologist emoji"></p>
<p>Previously we were deploying this app in <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/">Amazon Web Services (AWS)</a>. However, we had some issues that made the app stop working there, in which we could not have access to the AWS environment to look at the logs, so as a temporary solution I decided to host the backend REST API on Heroku.</p>
<p>While we don’t have the app in production where we will potentially run the app on AWS, we can use Heroku to deploy the development version of the app. Although ever since I deployed to Heroku, I am amazed how this makes it easy to deploy the REST API and how anyone in the community can easily do this. Besides this, some weeks ago I discovered the <a href="https://devcenter.heroku.com/articles/github-integration-review-apps">Review App</a> feature which allows us to easily deploy an app for any PR sent to our repository (with a limit of the number of apps since I’m using free tier).</p>
<hr>
<p>I hope you enjoyed this blog post and learn about deploying apps into Heroku!</p>
<p>Interested in the project? You can reach us on <a href="https://github.com/anitab-org">GitHub</a> on <a href="https://anitab-org.zulipchat.com/">Zulip</a>.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Images of People of Color for content creation</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/images-of-poc-for-content-creation/"/>
    <updated>2020-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/images-of-poc-for-content-creation/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/woc-in-tech-chat-1.jpeg" alt="#WOCinTech Chat"></p>
<p>A couple of years ago I saw <a href="https://peopleofcolorintech.com/articles/where-to-find-free-stock-photos-with-people-of-color/">this great blog post</a> from <a href="https://peopleofcolorintech.com/">peopleofcolorintech.com</a> about stock photos with people of color in it. I found this amazing! I never thought about using my blog posts or other types of public content to spread more visual representations of people of color.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://peopleofcolorintech.com/articles/where-to-find-free-stock-photos-with-people-of-color/">Where To Find Free Stock Photos With People of Color - POCIT</a></li>
</ul>
<p>After reading this, I became aware of the existence of pictures/illustrations I could use that include people of color in online content such as blogs, presentations, promotion flyers, etc. I understood I could use them as a way to increase the representation of women of color in online content, more specifically related to the Tech industry.</p>
<p>Since I became aware of this when I include pictures of people in my blog posts I try to always include people of color on it.</p>
<p>Here are three resources that I am always aware of when looking at stock photos for my blog posts:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/wocintechchat">Women of color in tech chat</a></li>
<li><a href="https://createherstock.com/">CreateHER Stock</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.blackillustrations.com/">Illustration of Black people</a></li>
</ul>
<p>I mostly use photos from <a href="http://wocintechchat.com/">WOCinTech Chat</a>, but I always have in mind all of these resources. In fact the image from this blog post is from #WOCinTech Chat.</p>
<p>Thank you for reading this, I hope you find these useful and consider using these resources when appropriate.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Open Source programs and initiatives</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/open-source-initiatives/"/>
    <updated>2020-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/open-source-initiatives/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p>In this blog post, I will mention some open source initiatives and programs that can help you get started or more involved with Open Source.</p>
<h2>Google Summer of Code</h2>
<p><a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code</a> (GSoC) is a program for university students to collaborate remotely with an open source organization during the summer. Students earn a stipend during this period. I participated in this initiative <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/archive/2018/projects/6592097335377920/">as a student</a> collaborating with <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a> organization. This is how I really got into understanding the spirit of Open Source and got to learn about it on many levels, initially as a contributor and then also as a maintainer. This year I am participating as a GSoC Admin with <a href="https://github.com/anitab-org">AnitaB.org Open Source</a> (previously Systers Open Source).</p>
<h2>Outreachy</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.outreachy.org/">Outreachy</a> is a similar program to Google Summer of Code, but instead of targeting university students, it supports participants from underrepresented groups in tech (not required to be in university). These are paid remote internships.</p>
<h2>24 Pull Requests</h2>
<p><a href="https://24pullrequests.com/">24 Pull Requests</a> happens during December. You can find on this website a list of issues ready to be taken or projects that are looking for contributors. I did my first contribution to open source, contributing to a markdown based project with resources for people looking for jobs (<a href="https://github.com/fvcproductions/hire-me/pull/9">my PR #9</a>).</p>
<h2>Google Code-in</h2>
<p><a href="https://codein.withgoogle.com/">Google Code-in</a> (GCI) is a competition for pre-university students between 13 and 17 years old. Participants have to complete tasks created by multiple Open Source Organizations in many categories, such as coding, documentation, research/outreach, design, and quality assurance. This year I had the pleasure to work as a GCI Mentor and witness creative work from participants. I really like that this program does not focus on coding contributions and explicitly promotes different types of contributions.</p>
<h2>Hacktoberfest</h2>
<p><a href="https://hacktoberfest.digitalocean.com/">Hacktoberfest</a> happens during the month of October. This is a great way for people to give back to open source during the month of October, just like 24 Pull Requests. You can win Hacktoberfest t-shirts once you submit a 4 amount of pull requests. I never participated as a contributor, but I did as a maintainer when I labeled certain issues form the projects I maintain with “Hacktoberfest” label.</p>
<h2>Other programs and initiatives</h2>
<p>There are plenty of other programs that help people get into open source, a few examples are <a href="https://railsgirlssummerofcode.org/">Rails Girls Summer of Code</a>, <a href="https://developers.google.com/season-of-docs/">Season of Docs</a>, etc.</p>
<p>There are some open source organizations that have their own programs that help people contribute in a structured way to their projects.</p>
<p>A while ago I found this collection of Open Source programs that has an extensive list of initiatives: <a href="https://github.com/tapaswenipathak/Open-Source-Programs">tapaswenipathak/Open-Source-Programs</a>.</p>
<p>If you are interested in finding open source projects but are not interested in participating in a specific program, it can still be useful to check projects and organizations that participate in these programs. Some of them can be well established and actively welcome contributions from the community (e.g.: <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/organizations">organizations accepted on GSoC</a>).</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>2019 Review</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/2019-review/"/>
    <updated>2019-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/2019-review/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p>2019 was a very year full of good surprises for me! So I wanted to write this post so that I can look back to.</p>
<p>Here’s a summary of my personal and professional achievements (not in order):</p>
<ul>
<li>I performed my first international talk at <a href="https://community.anitab.org/event/hopperx1-london/">Hopperx1 London</a>!</li>
<li>I also co organized <a href="https://community.anitab.org/event/hopperx1-london/">Hopperx1 London</a> event, serving as a Co Chair for Open Source track.</li>
<li>I presented my first virtual event / webinar!</li>
<li>I co-presented a webinar 2 times!</li>
<li>I talked at 2 DevFests: DevFest Porto in the beginning of the year and DevFest Lisbon at the end of the year.</li>
<li>I moved to London in October 😱</li>
<li>I visited a country close to my 💚</li>
<li>I became an open source maintainer for more than a full year.</li>
<li>I was a <a href="https://codein.withgoogle.com/">Google Code-in</a> mentor for the same project I proposed in <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">GSoC</a> 2018.</li>
<li>I joined <a href="https://community.anitab.org/">AnitaB.org London community</a> as one of the Community Leaders.</li>
<li>I met incredible people that mentored and helped me personally and professionally.</li>
</ul>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Overcoming blockers about contributing to Open Source</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/overcoming-blockers-about-contributing-to-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2019-06-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/overcoming-blockers-about-contributing-to-open-source/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/overcoming-blocks-technologist.png" alt="woman on pc emoji"></p>
<p>Contributing to Open Source can be super intimidating. Back in 2016 I already knew about the idea of contributing Open Source software. But never actually got started until November 2017. This is when I did my first contribution. Even though I started then, it was after getting accepted into Google Summer Of Code 2018’s edition, that I learned a lot about contributing to Open Source.</p>
<h2>My first Open Source contributions</h2>
<p><img src="/images/overcoming-blocks-juggle.png" alt="woman juggling emoji"></p>
<p>For some time I wanted to contribute to Open Source but never actually took the steps to do it until I saw an initiative called <a href="https://24pullrequests.com/">24 Pull Requests</a>, which is about giving back to open source during the month of December.</p>
<p>During this virtual event, in 2017, I did my first Open Source contribution by adding a job board website to a repository with resources for people looking for a job, made of markdown files. My contribution is in the <a href="https://github.com/fvcproductions/hire-me/pull/9">pull request #22</a> that I submitted for <a href="https://github.com/fvcproductions/hire-me">fvcproductions/hire-me</a> project.</p>
<p>Then at the beginning of 2018, I started contributing to some projects as I was trying to apply to <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer Of Code</a> (GSoC), making these two contributions:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>I submitted <a href="https://github.com/opendatakit/collect/pull/1986">pull request #1986</a> to <a href="https://github.com/opendatakit/collect">opendatakit/collect</a> project, where I picked up work from another contributor’s contribution and completed the issue. This involved changing a line of text on an Android application.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I created <a href="https://github.com/systers/systers.github.io/issues/167">issue #167</a> reporting an improvement to <a href="http://systers.io">systers.io</a> website and then submitted <a href="https://github.com/systers/systers.github.io/pull/168">pull request #168</a>, changing the text for Slack community on the “Contact Us” page.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>So I started with small steps. Then in April 2018, I got into Google Summer of Code with <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Community</a> where I was able to learn much more about Open Source.</p>
<h2>Blockers to contribute to Open Source</h2>
<p><img src="/images/overcoming-blocks-facepalm.png" alt="woman facepalming emoji"></p>
<p>So while I was participating on Google Summer of Code and trying to find ways to involve the community on the <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/archive/2018/projects/6592097335377920/">Mentorship System project</a> I was working on, I remembered about what was keeping me from contributing to Open Source initially.</p>
<p>Then I created a short survey for newcomers of Systers Community so that I could understand what was some blockers from other members on contributing to Open Source.</p>
<p>After reading the answers given and blockers from my personal experience I gathered these blockers:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>How and where to start contributing;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Not seeing many beginner issues;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Not being confident with my skills;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Some projects seem too intimidating;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Lack of time to contribute to open source;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>What if I can’t finish something I committed myself to.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2>Overcoming Blockers on contributing</h2>
<p><img src="/images/overcoming-blocks-raise-hand.png" alt="woman raising hand emoji"></p>
<p>So after looking into the common blockers gathered, I started thinking about them, and if I could find a way to overcome them. So here is my perspective on these blockers.</p>
<h3>How and where to start contributing</h3>
<p>You can start with some initiatives just like I did with <a href="https://24pullrequests.com/">24 Pull Requests</a>. Some other examples are <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code</a>, <a href="https://www.outreachy.org/">Outreachy</a>, and <a href="https://hacktoberfest.digitalocean.com/">Hacktoberfest</a>.</p>
<p>You can find Open Source communities that can have a consistent organization and context among its projects, and a community of contributors who can help you get started. A good way to find these is through seeing <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/organizations/">accepted organizations at Google Summer Of Code</a>. These organizations may have well set up projects ready for you to contribute to. I found communities such as <a href="https://github.com/opendatakit/">Open Data Kit</a>, <a href="https://github.com/openfoodfacts">Open Food Facts</a> and <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers</a> here.</p>
<p>Regarding finding projects, you can look into the projects you use frequently (e.g.: open source library, social impact project, any piece of software you use, etc…). You can look at issues labeled as “first-timers-only”, “good first issue” and “help wanted”, since these are usually used to indicate that the issues are beginner friendly. You can also check <a href="https://up-for-grabs.net">Up For Grabs</a>, which has a list of projects targetted for new contributors, and also <a href="https://www.codetriage.com/">CodeTriage</a>.</p>
<p>There is an awesome guide on <a href="https://opensource.guide/how-to-contribute/">“How to Contribute to Open Source”</a> by <a href="https://opensource.guide/">opensource.guide</a>, that you can also take a look at.</p>
<h3>Not seeing many beginner issues</h3>
<p>As I said before, look out for issues labeled as “first timers only” and “good first issue” since these are specially targetted for new contributors. For example, whenever I can, I label issues like this for newcomers, at <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aopen+label%3A%22First+Timers+Only%22">systers/mentorship-backend</a> and <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-android/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aopen+label%3A%22First+Timers+Only%22">systers/mentorship-android</a> projects. Although these labels can be helpful don’t limit yourself to them, because some issues may not have these labels but are still doable for you.</p>
<p>You can always propose new issues, and if they’re valid then contribute to them. This is exactly what I did with my contribution to Systers.io website. <a href="https://github.com/systers/systers.github.io/issues/167">I created an issue and then fixed it.</a></p>
<p>If you really don’t find issues that you feel you can solve for the project you’re looking into, try to look at other projects for you to begin with.</p>
<h3>Not being confident with your skills</h3>
<p>Confidence comes with time… And you don’t have to know everything. Being a software developer, I wanted to start contributing with actual code, but my <a href="https://github.com/fvcproductions/hire-me/pull/9">first contribution consisted of editing markdown files.</a> Even though this wasn’t a feature added to a project in the form of code, my contribution could help people looking into resources for a job hunt. I was super happy with this first step towards getting started with contributing to Open Source.</p>
<p>My next contribution involved changing text being used on an Android application. Even though this seemed like a small change, it was totally a valid contribution. So having said this, I think you can start small while building up your confidence while you start contributing. Even small changes are valid contributions to advance a project.</p>
<p>By the end of the GSoC program with Systers community, I understood that thought my journey I was feeling a bit more confident as I contributed to the community.</p>
<h3>Some projects seem too intimidating</h3>
<p>I totally understand this, there are projects in Open Source, that I don’t feel prepared to look into, as much as I might have the curiosity to. I can think of open source programming languages or tools I use that have a large codebase.</p>
<p>Know that projects have documentation that can help you, so look out for that. Make sure you looked into the project’s documentation, that can be on the Wiki (e.g.: GitHub Wiki), on a documentation folder together with the code, discussions on forums or on the issues comments’ section. Documentation can be scattered in multiple places. Also, it takes time to understand a project you never worked on, you may have to spend some time looking into the code and setting it up to understand the project (if you’re contributing with code).</p>
<p>Besides looking into the available Documentation, you can always reach out to the community and maintainers from the project, if you really feel stuck, so that they can provide resources to better understand the project.</p>
<h3>Lack of time to contribute</h3>
<p>Everyone has their own lives going on, with their own commitments. You have to think about how much you want to be involved with Open Source, and the “why”. Is this worth your time contributing to a specific project? Is it to give back to a project you care about? How much time can you actually give for this? What are your motivations? After you understand these you’ll have to think about how to incorporate this into your schedule and how to prioritize this.</p>
<p>Why not start with baby steps, both on the time, and the task you’ll work on. You can try to allocate a period of time, per week, to work on Open Source projects per week (e.g.: 1 to 2 hours on Sundays, 1 hour every day, …). You can also start working on low effort issues like I did for my first contribution. This can help you get acquainted with a usual open source workflow (e.g.: fork -&gt; clone -&gt; work -&gt; submit pull request) and help you get into a habit.</p>
<p>For me, it really helps to contribute to something I care about and want to see grow. Also, I enjoy a lot maintaining a project and making it accessible to newcomers to Open Source (e.g.: by creating issues with “first timers only” label in mind). I also enjoy giving back to the community that I worked with during GSoC.</p>
<h3>What if you can’t finish something you committed yourself to</h3>
<p>What if you commit to work on an issue and then you aren’t able to finish it, either because you lost interest for the issue, or aren’t able to finish it in the time you set yourself to do it, or its not appropriate for your current skill level… no matter the reason, this can happen.</p>
<p>If you’re getting initially stuck in the issue you’re trying to solve, it helps to ask questions to the community and read the documentation available to you.</p>
<p>If you really feel you have to give up on it, don’t just abandon it. Give notice to projects owners, maintainers and the community, that you won’t be working on it anymore, thus giving the opportunity to someone else to solve it. You can let them know by leaving comments on the issue you committed to. This is totally OK! Also if you already have some work on it that can help the next contributor, share that. By doing this, you’ll make the maintainer’s life easier, because they will know that another issue is available to be assigned to another contributor.</p>
<p><img src="/images/overcoming-blocks-wave.png" alt="wave hand emoji"></p>
<p>Hope you enjoyed this article and find getting started with open source a lot less intimidating!</p>
<p>To find more information about open source, I find <a href="https://opensource.guide/">opensource.guide</a> website to be a very good resource to all things related to open source.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Resources to motivate yourself to bootstrap products</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/resources-to-motivate-yourself-to-bootstrap-products/"/>
    <updated>2019-04-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/resources-to-motivate-yourself-to-bootstrap-products/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/woc-in-tech-chat-3.jpeg" alt="Credits to the amazing initiative www.wocintechchat.com"></p>
<p>One of the things that I’ve been paying attention to is the makers/bootstrappers/solo entrepreneurship movement. I’ve seen this movement taking off more last year. Although, of course, this is not a new thing, it is just something that has gotten more attention recently. This movement is about people who make products which are mainly self-funded. These products may start as a side project by founders and then lead to a profitable business.</p>
<p>You may see a lot of descriptions or definitions for these people who make self-funded products, such as indie makers, makers, bootstrappers, founders, entrepreneurs… These may all mean the same. What matters is that they’re building something and try to bring some value into society with their projects.</p>
<p>I’m very new to this environment, I’ve been thinking about this a lot, but haven’t yet given it my full attention. Nonetheless, discovering this movement was super important to me. Nowadays, we listen a lot about success stories from companies which became super profitable, that get a lot of social media attention. Discovering this movement made me look at startups in a different way. It made me believe more in myself, that I could make something on my own, without waiting for the perfect partner, or having to grow super fast, or having to get an idea to solve a big problem society faces. Looking at my own experiences, I’m able to come up with some ideas that would solve very specific issues I have, and other very few people might have. What I find valuable doesn’t have to be valuable at a massive scale. There are people out there making products that may not follow the popular convention of “Startup” that must have external investors and grow really fast, as I tend to hear. These products can bring value to a loyal and/or niche audience.</p>
<p>It’s important to know that one of the major factors that make people do this is to achieve financial freedom, which is totally understandable nowadays.</p>
<p>Maybe you’re curious about this too, but don’t know about these resources and how and where to start. Or maybe you aren’t aware of this concept’s popularity. Or maybe you just need that little push to start bringing your own project ideas to life.</p>
<h4>Communities</h4>
<p>I would like to highlight these two: Women Make and IndieHackers, that I’ve been following:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://womenmake.com/">Women Make</a> — This is an amazing and positive community open for all and meant to empower and highlight women makers. You can find more information about this community on their <a href="https://womenmake.com/">website</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/women_make_">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://medium.com/women-make">Medium publication</a>. I already learned a lot from this community and keep learning. Whenever I go there I get more and more inspired.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.indiehackers.com/">IndieHackers</a> — This is a community for “indie hackers”, all sort of entrepreneurs who want to share their experiences and learn from others. You can receive a digest of the articles posted there through their newsletter. This acts as a forum, you may see interviews or posts from members with engagement from the community.</li>
</ul>
<p>Here are some other interesting communities:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://makerskitchen.xyz/">MakerKitchen</a> — This is a Slack community for Makers. They have a lot of focused channels, where you share your experiences, get support and support others on their maker journey.</li>
<li><a href="https://t.me/solofounders">Solo Founders</a> — This is a Telegram group dedicated to solo founders.</li>
<li><a href="https://t.me/beginningcreators">Beginning Creators</a> — This is a Telegram group dedicated to beginning founders/creators.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Blogs</h4>
<p>These are blogs I really enjoy.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://makermag.com/">Maker Mag</a>, this is a recent blog made by makers for makers. I’ve been enjoying this a lot.</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/women-make">WomenMake Medium publication</a> is a place where members of Women Make community can share their stories.</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s important to notice that on <a href="https://www.indiehackers.com/">Indie Hackers</a> you can also find a lot of interesting posts.</p>
<p>I really really love the <a href="https://blog.stephsmith.io/you-dont-need-to-quit-your-job-to-make/">“You Don’t Need to Quit Your Job to Make”</a> blog post by Steph Smith, because it's so insightful about how we manage our time and define our priorities in life.</p>
<p>This next one is another interesting post about <a href="https://blog.cronhub.io/reflections-on-being-an-indie-hacker/">reflections on being an indie maker by Tigran</a>.</p>
<h4>Books</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://makebook.io/">MAKE — Bootstrapper’s Handbook by Pieter Levels</a></li>
<li><a href="https://makeandshine.com/">Make &amp; Shine — An Indie Maker’s Guide to Personal Branding by Anne-Laure Le Cunff</a></li>
</ul>
<h4>Podcasts</h4>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.startupsfortherestofus.com/">Startup for the rest of us</a> — I’ve discovered this podcast very recently and I find it awesome. It's really about two makers sharing their experiences and thoughts about the bootstrapping products and entrepreneurship.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.indiehackers.com/podcast">IndieHackers Podcast</a> — This podcast comes from the <a href="https://www.indiehackers.com">Indie Hackers</a> community, where you can listen to interviews from entrepreneurs and learn from their experience.</li>
<li><a href="https://makermag.com/podcast/">Trouble Makers</a> is a recent podcast from <a href="https://makermag.com/">MakerMag</a> blog about solo entrepreneurship.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><strong>Bonus Tip:</strong> If you subscribe to the newsletters from these resources, you can continue to get motivated by receiving tips and articles straight to your inbox.</p>
<p>Thank you for reading this post, I hope you learned something new or just got some source of motivation for you to make products you always wanted to do!</p>
<p>If you know more resources about this topic that can be useful to others, feel free to share them in the comments!</p>
<p><em>The image credits go to the amazing initiative <a href="https://www.wocintechchat.com">www.wocintechchat.com</a></em></p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>2018 Review</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/2018-review/"/>
    <updated>2018-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/2018-review/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p>2018 was a very important year for me! So I wanted to write this post so that I can look back to.</p>
<p>Here’s a summary of my personal and professional achievements (not in order):</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>I started my first full-time job in December!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I made my first talk in front of a live audience, about &quot;Getting Started with Open Source” at <a href="https://www.meetup.com/pt-BR/gdglisbon/events/254345727/">GDG Lisbon meetup</a> (20th September)!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I attended <a href="https://ghc.anitab.org/">Grace Hopper Celebration</a> in Houston, Texas and was <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a> representative at Open Source Day during the event! This was my first time being in America!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I presented my final MSc thesis and finished my Masters’ degree at <a href="https://tecnico.ulisboa.pt">Técnico Lisboa</a> (same time I finished my part time job of 2 years)!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I was accepted into the <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code (GSoC)</a> with the <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers community</a>, where I proposed <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/archive/2018/projects/6592097335377920/">Mentorship System</a>! I finished the program being nominated within the community as the Most Outstanding Student.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I traveled to Berlin with a friend!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I wrote a lot of blog posts (mainly about GSoC)!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Met the world of Open Source through GSoC and became a maintainer for the project I proposed!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I met some incredible people through the year!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I met some online communities, one of them being <a href="http://womenmake.com">WomenMake</a>, got very inspired by indie hacking and started believing I could build products for others on my own, without having to be VC backed. I just got inspired and continue to be!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I grew as a person, I evolved, I’m proud of what I am and how I feel now 🌱</p>
</li>
</ul>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Coming up with original ideas for Systers Open Source</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/coming-up-with-original-ideas-for-systers-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2018-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/coming-up-with-original-ideas-for-systers-open-source/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/woc-in-tech-chat-6.jpeg" alt="Source: #WOCinTech Chat photos"></p>
<p>This post is intended for anyone who wants to propose original ideas for <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a>. It can be within the <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com">Google Summer of Code</a> (GSoC) context or not, since this community does not do Open Source only during this program.</p>
<p>What I’ll say here is based on my experience within Systers Open Source community, from participating on Community Open Sessions, Projects Brainstorming sessions, conversations on Slack and so on.</p>
<h3>My personal advice</h3>
<p>It can be hard looking into other people’s problems and try to solve them. First I would advise you to try to look into your own experiences, just like I did. If you think about your experiences, you can see problems you want to solve. By coming up with an idea from problems you experience and understand, it is much easier to brainstorm features, look into edges cases and ways to solve a problem. Look for something you care about. You can also look at your surroundings, problems your friends or family experience.</p>
<p>What about projects that tackle or bring awareness and shine a light on social issues. For instance, I’ve seen someone start a discussion on how to create a project related to child abuse issue in a Community Open Session. You can think of projects that have a social impact, these are always welcome in my opinion.</p>
<p>When you do come with a new idea, do your research, for instance, look for similar solutions and think about: how are you proposing something better than what already exists? What is the main goal of the project?</p>
<p>Also, think if it fits Systers community mission. If you have doubts about the fit of the idea, share with the community anyways so that you can receive proper feedback.</p>
<p>If you check Systers Open Source website, you can understand more about what kind of projects the community welcomes. Here are some highlights from the website that can help you reflect:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We are committed to providing a friendly, safe, and welcoming environment for all, regardless of gender, sexual orientation, ability, ethnicity, socioeconomic status, work experience, or religion (or lack thereof).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(…)</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Our projects focus on impacting users and communities by improving their lives with technology.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3>Examples of original projects from Systers</h3>
<p>I’ll summarize 3 projects that started within the community, which you can find on GitHub.</p>
<h4>PowerUp</h4>
<p>PowerUp consists of female empowerment educational mobile game app that aims to teach young girls about reproductive health, conflict resolution, and self-esteem by navigating the life of their avatar. It works as a choose-your-own-adventure game with different scenarios to navigate through. This project started in GSoC 2015.</p>
<p>An interesting fact is that this originated other project ideas for GSoC 2018, consisting of tools to help create scenarios and content for story sequences for the Power Up mobile application. The GitHub repositories are <a href="https://github.com/systers/powerup-scenario-builder">systers/powerup-scenario-builder</a> and <a href="https://github.com/systers/powerup-story-designer">systers/powerup-story-designer</a> respectively.</p>
<p>You can learn more about this project on <a href="https://github.com/systers/powerup-android/wiki">its GitHub wiki documentation</a>.</p>
<p>Here are the links to the repositories of this project on GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/systers/powerup-android">systers/powerup-android</a> and <a href="https://github.com/systers/powerup-ios">systers/powerup-ios</a>.</p>
<h4>Mentorship System</h4>
<p>I proposed Mentorship System for GSoC 2018. I came up with this idea based on my own experiences, from mentoring first-year students in my college, from mentoring friends or other people I found that needed some sort of guidance, on career development topics. I wanted to do something from scratch that I identified myself with, so I thought about experiences I had, what could help me with the goal of reaching people that I could mentor outside of my circle of friends. This was something I wanted to solve for myself that gladly aligned with Systers mission and the minimum functional product was doable for Google Summer of Code 3 month duration.</p>
<p>Initially, I only proposed an Android application because that’s what I wanted to do and was comfortable with. Only after feedback from mentors that reviewed my proposal, I started thinking about the backend that was needed.</p>
<p>You can learn more about how I came up with this idea through <a href="https://medium.com/systers-opensource/mentorship-system-by-systers-52dbe1275d9f">“Mentorship System by Systers” blog post.</a></p>
<p>Here are the links to the repositories of this project on GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">systers/mentorship-backend</a> and <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-android">systers/mentorship-android</a>.</p>
<h4>Sysbot</h4>
<p>Sammy proposed Sysbot project for GSoC 2018. This project goal is to streamline the Open Source workflow of Systers community. Some of the functionalities are label issues, approve issues and PRs, allow contributors to claim and assign issues both from GitHub or Slack, guide newcomers with resources related to Open Source and the community.</p>
<p>Here is the link to the repository of this project on GitHub: <a href="https://github.com/systers/sysbot">systers/sysbot</a>.</p>
<h3>Special advice for GSoC proposals</h3>
<p><img src="/images/gsoc-logo.png" alt=""></p>
<p>When proposing an original idea make sure to explain well what you intend to do during the whole Google Summer of Code 3 month period. Consider these factors:</p>
<ul>
<li>If you have a lot of proposed features, think about which ones are required or a “nice to have”? Point them out.</li>
<li>How will your project idea benefit the community?</li>
<li>Which tech stack are you planning to use? If you’re proposing a game explain the idea, the tools you want to use. Is it for mobile? Is it for the web? Do you plan to use Unity?</li>
<li>Are you implementing a backend? Think about the system design and how you want to structure your data. Can you present UML diagrams, ER diagrams for the database?</li>
<li>If your project has visual components as a mobile or web app has, do present some user interface examples with mockup screens. I did a wireframe for Mentorship System.</li>
<li>If you have an idea to improve an already existing Systers project (even if archived), be detailed on what improvements you plan to for the project, and how you want to execute them.</li>
<li>Is your idea something you see yourself working on during 3 months or more? For instance, why am I still so involved with mentorship system? Because I want the project to have success! It’s a project that I care about, and I really liked bootstrapping the project and thinking about it from scratch.</li>
</ul>
<p>Whichever idea you choose, be clear about the technical requirements and aspects of your project idea. Be as complete as possible in your proposal’s timeline, project description, mission, etc.</p>
<p>Here’s <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1TkyLWbVyW9WHEoqFBwpE1GE6vDRf7aoITT6i7tBFKsw">my GSoC proposal for Mentorship System</a> as an example. This was initially created by me, although throughout the application phase, I improved this constantly according to mentors and the community's feedback.</p>
<hr>
<p><img src="/images/systers-os-logo.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Thank you for reading this post!</p>
<p>You can follow <a href="https://medium.com/systers-opensource">Systers Open Source Medium publication</a> to know updates from the community!</p>
<p>Check out <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source projects on GitHub</a> and find more about the <a href="http://systers.io/">Systers Open Source community</a>.</p>
<p><em>This first image credits goes to the amazing initiative <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/wocintechchat">#WOCinTech Chat photos</a>.</em></p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>GSoC with Systers Community Closure</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-with-systers-closure/"/>
    <updated>2018-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-with-systers-closure/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/gsoc-closure-cover.png" alt="final remarks image representing end of gsoc"></p>
<p>This year I was a <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code</a> student for <a href="http://systers.io/">Systers Community</a>. For a long time, I was interested in Open Source but I never managed to take off and start contributing for projects. This year I decided to apply for the second time and was accepted!</p>
<p>This year I decided to <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1TkyLWbVyW9WHEoqFBwpE1GE6vDRf7aoITT6i7tBFKsw">propose a new idea</a> so that I could participate in a project from scratch, work on something I could identify myself with and at the same time start contributing to Open Source within a community. So <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/archive/2018/projects/6592097335377920/">I proposed a Mentorship System.</a></p>
<h2>The Program</h2>
<p>The Mentorship System I proposed consists of an application that matches women in tech to mentor each other for a certain period of time. I wanted an application dedicated to anyone who was either new or already in the Tech industry, from any social-economic background, and from any stage of their career to help each other out. You can <a href="https://medium.com/systers-opensource/mentorship-system-by-systers-52dbe1275d9f">find out more about the idea and motivations in this post.</a></p>
<p>Once I got accepted, during the Community Bonding phase, I started enhancing the idea and planning with my mentors and the community what would be the first features that should be implemented for the backend. I also prepared the initial documentation for any interested member of the community to look up and learn more about the project.</p>
<p>Then during the Coding Phase, I started implementing the backend until it was stable enough to start the Android application. During the program, I got to be present and work in all areas of the Mentorship System, including UI Design, REST API design, implement the minimum features of the app, set up test cases, proper documentation to help the community be updated and learn about how to work within an Open Source community.</p>
<h2>Final Work Product</h2>
<p>The final product ended up being a <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">backend built with python</a> and an <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-android">Android client</a> of the Mentorship System, that make a minimum functional product.
These are the GitHub repositories I worked with:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-android">systers/mentorship-android</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">systers/mentorship-backend</a></li>
</ul>
<p>You can learn more about what I did during the program in my <a href="https://gist.github.com/isabelcosta/413e5a58529b7be9cdb57dddc08fec01">final report of my GSoC work</a>. At the moment the project is more evolved thanks to contributions from the open source community.</p>
<p>In the final week of the program, I did the final demonstration of my work on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xRZrdR47R-w">live on YouTube</a>.</p>
<h2>Achievements</h2>
<p>I learned a lot from this experience! I’m super proud of the work I did during GSoC. This was the first time I worked fully remote and with a global team, where I could only speak English (not my native language).</p>
<p>Now that some time has passed I can clearly see the impact this had in my life and career. Here are some highlights:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>I got to do a backend from scratch and learn about implementing REST APIs. This really helped me in a recent technical interview for my current job;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I learned a lot about open source and how to behave in open source communities, like Systers Open Source. This led me to want to share my learnings and do my first public talk at a <a href="https://www.meetup.com/pt-BR/gdglisbon/events/254345727/">meetup organized by Google Developers Group Lisbon</a>;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I went to <a href="https://ghc.anitab.org/">Grace Hopper Celebration</a> 2018 in Houston, Texas, represent Systers Open Source at Open Source Day event. My first time going to the United States of America!</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Now I have some public work I can show to demonstrate my skills. By public work I’m referring to code, issues I created, <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1TkyLWbVyW9WHEoqFBwpE1GE6vDRf7aoITT6i7tBFKsw">my GSoC proposal</a>, documentation, <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc">my blog posts</a>, etc;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I maintain the project I work for, by reviewing pull requests, creating new issues, discussing features and bugs with the community, improving documentation (when needed). Also through this, I can provide a friendly environment for beginners to contribute to open source;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I got to meet incredible people from the community. I grew professionally and personally by sharing and learning from others’ perspectives.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Finally, I was nominated by my peers, mentors, and admins, from Systers Community as the Most Outstanding student out of 11 students. Being recognized for my work during GSoC made me very happy since I was already proud of my personal achievements.</p>
<p>This is my Digital Certificate for my outstanding work during GSoC with Systers Community.</p>
<p><img src="/images/gsoc-closure-certificate-excellence.png" alt="Digital Certificate for my outstanding work during GSoC with Systers Community"></p>
<h2>Final Thoughts</h2>
<p>Even though the program as ended in August 22nd, I’m still part of the community and plan to continue to be. I am determined to continue this project and at the same time, use this to help people, who may be intimidated with Open Source, start contributing and start feeling less intimidated by it.</p>
<p>This was truly an awesome experience.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>How I set up Tinyproxy as a forward proxy and reverse proxy</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/setup-tinyproxy-as-forward-and-reverse-proxy/"/>
    <updated>2018-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/setup-tinyproxy-as-forward-and-reverse-proxy/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><a href="https://tinyproxy.github.io/">Tinyproxy</a> is a light-weight HTTP/HTTPS proxy daemon for POSIX operating systems, which is <a href="https://github.com/tinyproxy/tinyproxy">open source on Github</a>.</p>
<p>I tried out this tool to set up a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proxy_server">forward proxy</a> on the client side of the communication and a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reverse_proxy">reverse proxy</a> on the server side. I wanted to use this so that I could do experiments on the network between the forward proxy and reverse proxy, without the client and server’s involvement.</p>
<p>Reverse proxies are mostly used as a load balancer, where we connect with a reverse proxy which then decides to which machine it should send the request.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“(…) With reverse proxying it’s possible to make a number of sites appear as if they were part of a single site (…)”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>from the manual of the configuration file of Tinyproxy.</p>
<h2>Requirements</h2>
<p>The following requirements represent what I used in my experiment:</p>
<ul>
<li>An image with a Linux OS distribution — I used a <a href="https://www.debian.org/">Debian</a> GNU/Linux 8.9 (Jessie);</li>
<li>4 virtual machines to serve as client, forward proxy, reverse proxy and server — I used <a href="https://www.virtualbox.org/">VirtualBox</a> to run these machines, with the Debian’s OS image;</li>
<li>The server has to run a Web Server — I used <a href="https://httpd.apache.org/">Apache HTTP server</a>, to return the default HTML page saying “It works!”;</li>
<li>The client has to have a browser or a command-line tool installed such as <a href="https://curl.haxx.se/">curl</a>, to do HTTP requests;</li>
<li>The forward and reverse proxy machines should have <a href="https://tinyproxy.github.io/">tinyproxy</a> installed — Next I’ll show how to install it on the Debian machines. The version I used was 1.8.3.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Test architecture</h2>
<p><img src="/images/tinyproxy-trial-architecture.png" alt="Test architecture for the experiment"></p>
<p>I created <a href="https://github.com/isabelcosta/testing-tiny-proxy">isabelcosta/testing-tiny-proxy</a> repository on Github with the configuration files needed to run both roles of forward proxy and reverse proxy.</p>
<h2>Network Configuration</h2>
<p>VirtualBox lets you configure the network settings of the virtual machines. I used Nat Network setting which allowed me to have all the machines within the same network. These were the IP assigned to each machine.</p>
<ul>
<li>Client — 10.0.2.33</li>
<li>Forward Proxy — 10.0.2.35</li>
<li>Reverse Proxy — 10.0.2.36</li>
<li>Server — 10.0.2.34</li>
</ul>
<p>These IP addresses will be important, because they will appear in the examples of how to test the system.</p>
<h2>Install Tinyproxy</h2>
<p>To install Tinyproxy, you have to type the following command into the forward and reverse proxy machines’s terminal:</p>
<pre><code>apt-get install tinyproxy
</code></pre>
<h2>Setting up the system</h2>
<p>Tinyproxy works according to configuration files. I wrote two configurations, one for the forward proxy and another for the reverse proxy.</p>
<p><strong>Forward proxy configuration files:</strong></p>
<pre><code>## forwardproxy.conf -- tinyproxy daemon configuration file

User nobody
Group nogroup

Port 8888
Listen 10.0.2.35
BindSame yes

Timeout 600

DefaultErrorFile &quot;/usr/share/tinyproxy/default.html&quot;
StatFile &quot;/usr/share/tinyproxy/stats.html&quot;
Logfile &quot;/var/log/tinyproxy/tinyproxy.log&quot;
#Syslog On
LogLevel Info
PidFile &quot;/var/run/tinyproxy/tinyproxy.pid&quot;

# Comment to use only the forward proxy
# Uncomment to forward the traffic to the reverse proxy
#Upstream 10.0.2.36:8888

MaxClients 100
MinSpareServers 2
MaxSpareServers 5
StartServers 2
MaxRequestsPerChild 0

Allow 127.0.0.1
Allow 10.0.2.0/24

ViaProxyName &quot;tinyproxy1&quot;

ConnectPort 8888
ConnectPort 80

# The following two ports are used by SSL.
ConnectPort 443
ConnectPort 563
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Reverse proxy configuration files:</strong></p>
<pre><code>## reverseproxy.conf -- tinyproxy daemon configuration file

User nobody
Group nogroup

Port 8888
Listen 10.0.2.36

BindSame yes
Timeout 600

StatFile &quot;/usr/share/tinyproxy/stats.html&quot;
Logfile &quot;/var/log/tinyproxy/tinyproxy.log&quot;
#Syslog On
LogLevel Info
PidFile &quot;/var/run/tinyproxy/tinyproxy.pid&quot;

MaxClients 5
MinSpareServers 2
MaxSpareServers 5
StartServers 2

MaxRequestsPerChild 0

Allow 127.0.0.1
Allow 10.0.2.0/24
Allow 10.0.2.35

ViaProxyName &quot;tinyproxy2&quot;

ConnectPort 8888
ConnectPort 80

# The following two ports are used by SSL.
ConnectPort 443
ConnectPort 563

ReversePath &quot;/test/&quot; &quot;http://10.0.2.34:80/&quot;
#ReversePath &quot;/&quot; &quot;http://10.0.2.34:80/&quot;
ReversePath &quot;/wired/&quot; &quot;http://www.wired.com/&quot;

ReverseOnly Yes
ReverseMagic Yes
ReverseBaseURL &quot;http://10.0.2.36:8888/&quot;
</code></pre>
<p>To run tinyproxy with a specific configuration just do the following:</p>
<pre><code>tinyproxy -c &lt;configuration-file&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>E.g.: tinyproxy -c forwardproxy.conf</p>
<h2>Testing the system</h2>
<p>First make sure that the server is running accordingly and you can access the server with the following command, from any of the machines, since all of them are in the same network. You can test this using <a href="https://curl.haxx.se/">curl</a> command line tool or on a browser:</p>
<pre><code>curl http://10.0.2.34:80/ 
</code></pre>
<p>Now to test the whole system, if you want to use curl you can type this on the client machine console:</p>
<pre><code>curl -v --proxy http://10.0.2.35:8888 http://10.0.2.36:8888/
</code></pre>
<p>This is the output of the previous command:</p>
<pre><code>root@debian:/home/debian# curl -v --proxy http://10.0.2.35:8888 http://10.0.2.36:8888
* Rebuilt URL to: http://10.0.2.36:8888/
* Hostname was NOT found in DNS cache
*   Trying 10.0.2.35...
* Connected to 10.0.2.35 (10.0.2.35) port 8888 (#0)
&gt; GET http://10.0.2.36:8888/ HTTP/1.1
&gt; User-Agent: curl/7.38.0
&gt; Host: 10.0.2.36:8888
&gt; Accept: */*
&gt; Proxy-Connection: Keep-Alive
&gt; 
&lt; HTTP/1.1 200 OK
&lt; Via: 1.0 tinyproxy2 (tinyproxy/1.8.3), 1.1 tinyproxy1 (tinyproxy/1.8.3)
&lt; Last-Modified: Mon, 11 Jun 2007 18:53:14 GMT
&lt; Date: Tue, 12 Dec 2017 23:01:37 GMT
&lt; Content-Type: text/html
&lt; ETag: &quot;2d-432a5e4a73a80&quot;
&lt; Set-Cookie: yummy_magical_cookie=/; path=/
* Server Apache/2.4.29 (Unix) is not blacklisted
&lt; Server: Apache/2.4.29 (Unix)
&lt; Content-Length: 45
&lt; Accept-Ranges: bytes
&lt; 
&lt;html&gt;&lt;body&gt;&lt;h1&gt;It works!&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;
* Connection #0 to host 10.0.2.35 left intact
</code></pre>
<p>Another way to see that this is working, is by using <a href="https://www.wireshark.org/">Wireshark</a> tool. This tool allows you to see network traffic. Before testing the system start running Wireshark. By testing in a local network you can see the whole traffic from the client to the server. After requesting and receiving the response from the server, if you filter the Wireshark captures by “http”, you should see a result similar to the following image.</p>
<p><img src="/images/tinyproxy-trial-wireshark.png" alt="Wireshark capture of the communication between the client and the server, passing through the proxies."></p>
<p>In this <a href="https://www.wireshark.org/">Wireshark</a> capture you can see the traffic in both directions: client ↔ forward proxy ↔ reverse proxy ↔ server.</p>
<p>To check log file and the forward and reverse proxies, you can type the following on either the machines:</p>
<pre><code>cat /var/log/tinyproxy/tinyproxy.log
</code></pre>
<p>If you want to test this in another way you can change the proxies’ configuration files on <a href="https://github.com/isabelcosta/testing-tiny-proxy">isabelcosta/testing-tiny-proxy</a> repository.</p>
<h2>Tips &amp; Notes</h2>
<ul>
<li>If you want to set up other paths you can do it with the “ReversePath” keyword. E.g.: ReversePath “/test” “http://10.0.2.34:80/” — in this way you can access the server by typing “http://10.0.2.36:8888/test”</li>
<li>I was always getting the error 400 Bad Request, because I was using this tool in the wrong way. I was using curl to connect with the server as the endpoint instead of the reverse proxy. The reverse proxy does not work as a forward proxy, so don’t use the “upstream” keyword to forward the traffic to the reverse proxy.</li>
</ul>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Google Summer of Code | Coding Period | Week 12</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-12/"/>
    <updated>2018-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-12/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-12-cover.png" alt=""></p>
<p>This week — July 30 to August 5 — was the 12th week of the coding period of <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code (GSoC)</a> with <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a>. If you want to know more about this you can read the <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc/intro-to-google-summer-of-code-with-systers-open-source-dbdaa92bd189">introduction to my journey</a>, <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc">my latest weekly blog posts</a> or <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/wiki/GSoC-2018-Isabel-Costa#weekly-status-report-for-week-12">my weekly status report</a> for this week.</p>
<hr>
<p>Although I have to improve the documentation, I also have to improve the final product, in this case, the Android application, and prepare for the final demonstration of my GSoC work for next week (6th-10th August).</p>
<p>At this moment, the Android application is my biggest concern because I really wanted to have a good Minimum Functional Product at the end of the <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">GSoC program</a>, and this part of the work was delayed. I spent a lot of time <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">developing the backend</a>. This is not a bad thing since the backend had to be stable before starting the <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-android">frontend development with the mobile application</a>. During this program, I noticed that time estimations for development are not easy at all. In my past job, I notice this as well. We sometimes overestimate or underestimate the time to develop a feature. A lot of things can vary this time of development. Some examples can be some inexperience I might have with a certain technology or problem that I have to solve. Also, the time that I might wait for my PRs to be reviewed, then improved and merged. Developing software using best practices may take some time and that’s ok. Best practices such as having people review your work before merging into the main branch can avoid bugs and single accountability of the code merged by the developer of the pull request.</p>
<p>When I proposed this project idea for GSoC, I wanted to have the mobile application and the backend as complete as possible at the end of the program. But at the same time, I wanted this to be an open source project, that could be contributed by open source contributors so that this wouldn’t depend totally on me to work out well. Part of what I tried to do during the program, was to promote the project within the community to welcome people to get involved in the project. In this way, I can get the community interested in contributing to the project and build this up into a great Mentorship System.</p>
<h3>Development tasks</h3>
<p>Regarding the backend, we had to restructure the response from Mentorship Relation API. We were only sending the id of the users and for the UI screens that shows the Mentorship Relations, we show the name of the users. So I submitted <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/123">PR #123</a> on <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">systers/mentorship-backend</a> repository to fix the API response.</p>
<p>This week I configured for the first time, a project to have <a href="https://travis-ci.org/">Travis CI</a> support. I did this for the Android application. I created the .travis.yml so that every time we push new code to the mobile application, Travis builds the application to see if everything goes right and the build does not fail. In this way, we can avoid pushing code that does not compile. One thing that really helped me to do this was looking into other open source projects’ .travis.yml from the community. For this task, I submitted <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-android/pull/16">PR #16</a>.</p>
<p>Regarding the <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-android">Android application</a>, I submitted <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-android/pull/17">PR #17</a> with the initial screens, Register, Login screen and Main authenticated screen with a bottom navigation. While I was waiting for this to be merged, I continued developing other UIs using <a href="https://developer.android.com/reference/android/support/constraint/ConstraintLayout">ConstraintLayout</a>. I also submitted yesterday <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-android/pull/25">PR #25</a> with the Members List and Member Profile implementation.</p>
<p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-12-members-list.png" alt="Members List and Member Profile UI submitted on PR #25 (2 screens on right are scrolled down)"></p>
<p>Finally, this next week, starting August 6th, I, my mentors and my admin will wrap up my GSoC work. After this, I will post a final weekly post with some reflection about the opportunity to participate in this program.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Google Summer of Code | Coding Period | Week 11</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-11/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-11/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-11-cover.png" alt=""></p>
<p>This week — July 23 to July 29 — was the eleventh week of the coding period of <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code (GSoC)</a> with <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a>. If you want to know more about this you can read the <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc/intro-to-google-summer-of-code-with-systers-open-source-dbdaa92bd189">introduction to my journey</a>, <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc">my latest weekly blog posts</a> or <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/wiki/GSoC-2018-Isabel-Costa#weekly-status-report-for-week-11">my weekly status report</a> for this week.</p>
<h3>Documentation</h3>
<p>I tried to maintain the documentation as complete as possible during the GSoC program in many ways. This is a very important part of our work since this is open source, other contributors might want to contribute to the project or if we ever become inactive, others can continue our work within the community. I take a lot of notes about everything we discuss on the project weekly meetings so that our discussions are properly documented for other members of the community to see. I also created two docs during the Community Bonding period, regarding the <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1qDTJK-ItAaek5ZBSLd4i8ShxLDcU5D2b4ZdIBTNxEJM/edit?usp=sharing">Backend</a> and <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1RhYMjyd1yhAWarO7spRWOYm-KNgFsO9rNgO6ssnEC-o/edit?usp=sharing">Application</a> features on Google Docs to let others know more about the project’s idea, features, system design decisions and implementation.</p>
<p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-11-documentation.png" alt="Documentation organization on Google Drive"></p>
<p>The past two weeks the GSoC students presented a live demo for the work completed on Phase I &amp; II. This was for documentation purposes and to serve as training for the final demo which is going to be live on Youtube at the end of the GSoC. I got good feedback from my presentation and advises. One interesting thing was that one GSoC student that attended my live demo, <a href="https://github.com/BaaniLeen">Baani</a>, showed me that when I tested the backend while presenting, it was much more clear how to test for quality assurance. This is something I tried to incentive others to do, but at that moment I understood that I had to be more clear and provide more documentation perhaps regarding testing the backend. I created a Google Docs while back with test cases for each feature to guide contributors and testers, as well a step by step guide on how to login into the Mentorship System using the Swagger UI. Also regarding what to actually test, is normal if new contributors don’t know enough about the project to come up with test cases to test the project features so I may have to add more documentation on that.</p>
<p>Another task I did this week, was creating the <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/wiki/How-to-Contribute">“How to Contribute” Wiki page</a> for <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">systers/mentorship-backend</a> GitHub repository regarding ways that a new contributor can help the Mentorship System. These ways include much more than coding, this page includes sections for documentation, quality assurance, outreach and incentive to participate in Slack discussions regarding the project. I also created a wiki for the Android project, which is still a bit empty but will surely be improved as the project progresses.</p>
<p>As another part of documentation tasks, <a href="https://drive.google.com/open?id=1Nkhrxjbuh3_Z_rCww4Z2dQWgkCg7tiiZ">I saved all the UI designs, I made using JustInMind, on the Google Drive folder</a> where students may save their work. I did this by using <a href="https://www.justinmind.com/support/how-to-export-your-wireframes-to-image-files/">a feature provided by the tool that allows me to export the designs as images</a>. This is crucial because if we ever lose access to the <a href="https://www.justinmind.com/usernote/tests/35756605/35766303/35777319/index.html">JustInMind UI prototype link</a>, we’ll still have the designs.</p>
<h3>User Interface (UI) Design Hacks</h3>
<p>This week I continued to work on the Android application and one of the tasks I had to do was the bottom navigation. For the Bottom Navigation with 5 items, I used 4 icons of the <a href="https://material.io/tools/icons/">Material Design icons</a>. The one that was not from Material, I created it inspired by a GSoC student’s suggestion that shared a similar image, but I felt that wasn’t totally aligned with Material Design, so I created my own version of it (in PNG format with copy, paste, and cuts). This icon is shown in the next image, it is the middle one with the label “Relation” that represents the current mentorship relation a User is involved with.</p>
<p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-11-bottom-nav.png" alt="Bottom navigation designed for Mentorship Android Application"></p>
<p>To use this in the Android Application I wanted an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scalable_Vector_Graphics">SVG</a> icon format so I created the image again so that I could later export to a valid SVG file. I created this with 2 arrows on <a href="http://draw.io">draw.io</a> and <a href="https://material.io/tools/icons/?icon=person&amp;style=baseline">Material Design’s person icon</a>. Once the image was edited I used <a href="https://inkscape.org/">Inkscape</a> to resize and play with the icon, but then I was having some problems so I took a crop at the image and used <a href="https://www.online-convert.com/">Online Converter</a> to convert the icon to an SVG. Then I copied again to <a href="https://inkscape.org/">Inkscape</a>, saved and then I imported the resulting SVG file to Android Studio.</p>
<p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-11-vector-asset.png" alt="Importing the SVG icon to Android Studio"></p>
<h3>Developing Android application</h3>
<p>I continued learning about Android Development using MVVM, RxJava, and android architecture components. I tried to learn best practices of developing an application with these components and architecture. I had multiple 1:1s with Murad, one of my mentors that showed me areas of improvement on the code I was developing to bootstrap the project.</p>
<p>Regarding UI development, at first, I was hesitant about using Constraint Layouts because I just didn’t know how to use them. First times I used them I didn’t understand if I was doing things right. Then I figured that this was used by manipulating views with drag and drop on design tool from Android Studio, so I decided to give it a real try since my mentor advised me to use them.</p>
<p>I wanted to know why and how I should use Constraint Layout so I researched about it and came across a really nice talk on this topic, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rzmB3UxxhaA">“Mastering ConstraintLayout in Android”</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/riggaroo">Rebecca Franks</a>.<br>
This made me feel more comfortable about using these layouts and understanding that this avoids nested views, therefore, improving performance when Android draws the UI.</p>
<p>This Sunday I tried Constraint Layouts for a User Profile view which is used to show and edit a User’s profile. This next image represents the screen designed for the User profile, implemented with ConstaintLayouts using textInputLayouts with editTexts and switches.</p>
<p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-11-constraint-layout.png" alt="Editing User profile screen Constraint Layouts on Android Studio"></p>
<p>A quick shout-out to the community, I shared a bit of my frustration and inexperience with these types of layouts and got lots of helpful responses from community members.</p>
<p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-11-ask-doubts.png" alt="Asking doubts on Slack"></p>
<h3>Time management</h3>
<p>Usually, for project meetings, I start preparing the agenda over the week with questions, ideas, doubts, and updates about the Mentorship System (both backend and Android) to discuss with the admin and the mentors, and sometimes we go over the time (1 hour). This week I tried out something that really surprised me in a good way. I planned the time for the meeting, to discuss general briefing (10 min), the Android application (30 min), and the backend (20 min). What surprised me was that in the end there was one minute left and we had already discussed everything on the agenda. I was so excited about having structured the meeting and giving time estimation for each part and this working out.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Google Summer of Code | Coding Period | Week 10</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-10/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-10/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-10-cover.png" alt=""></p>
<p>This week — July 16 to July 22 — was the tenth week of the coding period of <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code (GSoC)</a> with <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a>. If you want to know more about this you can read the <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc/intro-to-google-summer-of-code-with-systers-open-source-dbdaa92bd189">introduction to my journey</a>, <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc">my latest weekly blog posts</a> or <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/wiki/GSoC-2018-Isabel-Costa#weekly-status-report-for-week-10">my weekly status report</a> for this week.</p>
<h3>Implementation decisions</h3>
<p>This week a lot of the time I dedicated to studying <a href="https://8thlight.com/blog/uncle-bob/2012/08/13/the-clean-architecture.html">Clean Architecture</a> to apply to the <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-android">Mentorship System Android application</a>. We first thought of implementing the Android application using Clean Architecture with Kotlin. After following some video tutorials and started learning about the architecture and I noticed that it involved a lot of module separation, a lot of boilerplate by creating entity mappers and interfaces, which for the first version of the Android application, that has to be developed with the minimum features for a minimum functional product, seemed too complex. At this moment, I have 2 to 3 weeks to build the application so this architecture wouldn’t be a good fit because of the learning curve. So I decided to follow a simpler approach by experimenting with another Android Design architecture besides <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model%E2%80%93view%E2%80%93presenter">Model View Presenter (MVP)</a>. I’m now using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model%E2%80%93view%E2%80%93viewmodel">Model View View Model (MVVM)</a> also with Kotlin language.</p>
<p>As for Android library third-party libraries, I’m using Retrofit for communicating with a remote server. I’m also learning about <a href="https://github.com/ReactiveX/RxJava">RxJava</a> which seems to be a very powerful tool used by Android developers, that would introduce a new programming paradigm to the community, reactive programming. Besides this tool I’m already taking advantage of Android Architecture components such as <a href="https://developer.android.com/topic/libraries/architecture/viewmodel">ViewModel</a> and <a href="https://developer.android.com/topic/libraries/architecture/livedata">LiveData</a>, also I’m using <a href="https://developer.android.com/topic/libraries/data-binding/">DataBinding</a> with <a href="https://developer.android.com/topic/libraries/architecture/viewmodel">ViewModel</a>. In the future for application persistence, as discussed in an Android general meeting within the community, we will use Room for the database.</p>
<p>This week I had a meeting with one of my mentors Murad where we discussed potential better ways to save Tasks related to a Mentorship Relation into the Database. I will study more about that but basically, Murad advised me of a potential scalability problem since tasks are entities that can be easily created in abundance for each relation, this can cause problems because to get tasks from a relation we will have to search in the whole table of all tasks of the system, to get all the tasks that are related to the specific relation. We agreed that I would search a bit on that to find a better solution that saving a task as a single item in a Tasks table.</p>
<h3>Shout outs to great work from the development community</h3>
<p>I was an Android Developer for 2 years at a company until April this year, then I started developing <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">backend</a> with <a href="http://flask.pocoo.org/">flask</a> and <a href="https://www.python.org/">python</a>. To refresh my memory and get back to Android development, by learning about design architectures and tools used by Android developers, I’m googling a lot! I found a lot of good resources, such as videos, talks, blog posts and open source projects, that have a huge role in my learning journey. So here are some shout-outs to these resources.</p>
<ul>
<li>Android Architecture Blueprints project: <a href="https://github.com/googlesamples/android-architecture">googlesamples/android-architecture</a> repository on GitHub with a lot of Android design architecture patterns implemented;</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/google-developers/livedata-with-snackbar-navigation-and-other-events-the-singleliveevent-case-ac2622673150">LiveData with SnackBar, Navigation and other events (the SingleLiveEvent case)</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/ppvi">Jose Alcérreca</a> — helped me a lot understanding <a href="https://developer.android.com/topic/libraries/architecture/livedata">LiveData</a> android architecture component;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ericmaxwell2003/MvvmTipCalculator">ericmaxwell2003/MvvmTipCalculator</a> GitHub project by <a href="https://twitter.com/emmax">Eric Maxwell</a>;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/bufferapp/clean-architecture-components-boilerplate">bufferapp/clean-architecture-components-boilerplate</a> by <a href="https://github.com/bufferapp">Buffer</a>;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/isabelcosta/MoviesApp/">isabelcosta/MoviesApp</a> GitHub project made by Me — this was my first application coded 100% with Kotlin app, to refresh my memory about the programming language;</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q4eK3VFhnA0">Advanced Networking with RxJava + Retrofit</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/sddamico">Stephen D’Amico</a> at Droidcon NYC 2017 conference;</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XLH2v9deew0">Intro to RxJava</a>, a talk by <a href="https://twitter.com/runchristinarun">Christina Lee</a> at 360|AnDev 2016 conference— really nice talk about <a href="https://github.com/ReactiveX/RxJava">RxJava</a> which made me feel a bit less intimidated about <a href="https://github.com/ReactiveX/RxJava">RxJava</a>;</li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/corebuild-software/simple-android-mvvm-using-rx-and-kotlin-9769a91b03ef">Simple Android MVVM using RX and Kotlin</a>, a blog post by <a href="https://twitter.com/ovy9086">Ovidiu Latcu</a>;</li>
<li><a href="https://www.thomaskioko.com/android-architecture-components-part-2-dependency-injection/">Android Architecture Components Part 2 — Dependency Injection</a>, a blog post by <a href="https://twitter.com/code_wizard">Thomas Kioko</a> — even though I might not use <a href="https://google.github.io/dagger/">Dagger</a>, for now, this really gave me the click I needed after through the last year reading and watching resources about <a href="https://google.github.io/dagger/">Dagger</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>Ultimately I found a lot of resources that helped me in one way or another, even if I only used the knowledge provided from just a paragraph of text or a gist of code. I cannot point to all the resources but I found these that I shared very helpful.</p>
<h3>Development tasks</h3>
<p>This week my development tasks revolved around fixing bugs that were found by new contributors to the project during Quality Assurance testing.</p>
<p>I did my first full review <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/105">PR #105</a> from a new contributor on Mentorship System backend repository. I say full review because I’ve made some comments on other PRs from the community, but in this case, I was fully aware of the project so I made suggestions I considered important and needed for the issue that the PR was solving, like tests, extra data validation, commit message style, etc. It was really insightful giving suggestions and areas for improvements of other contributor’s work.</p>
<p>I also submitted the following pull requests:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/95">PR #95</a> regarding <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/issue/94">issue #94</a> to solve user registration data validation;</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/107">PR #107</a> to fix a bug of validation when updating the User’s profile (<a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/issue/97">issue #97</a>) found by a newcomer!</li>
</ul>
<h3>Design tasks</h3>
<p>I improved the <a href="https://www.justinmind.com/usernote/tests/35756605/35766303/35777319/index.html">Mentorship System UI prototype</a> hosted on <a href="https://www.justinmind.com/">JustInMind</a>. I had discussions with my mentors on the project weekly and with my project manager in the Office hours, about what would be the best UI for a good user experience for the users regarding the Tasks screen. From the screen alternatives that I shared last week with the community, my project manager, May, did a poll to know what option was preferred.</p>
<p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-10-ui-design.png" alt=""></p>
<p>The majority of the voters chose option 2, so I updated the UI prototype to fit the community’s feedback.</p>
<h3>New mentor and working with other GSoC student</h3>
<p>This week I had a new mentor, <a href="https://github.com/roopalJazz">Roopal</a>, assigned to me to help us in this last phase of development. We had our first 1:1 for us to meet each other and to keep <a href="https://github.com/roopalJazz">Roopal</a> on the loop of all the development and things to know about the project which could be important for a mentor.</p>
<p>A fellow GSoC student, <a href="https://github.com/sammy1997">Sombuddha Chakravarty</a>, that is developing a bot, <a href="https://github.com/systers/sysbot">Sysbot</a>, used on Slack and GitHub to help mentors and community members interact with <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a>, integrated the bot in the <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">systers/mentorship-backend</a> GitHub repository. So I took advantage of the Ask Me Anything session Sammy was hosting, to have a quick 1:1 where I could learn about the commands that I and my mentors should know to have a good workflow on GitHub in terms of assigning, approving issues and sending valid PRs that would not be closed by the bot.</p>
<p>I hosted more AMA sessions for newcomers to come and ask questions regarding open source in general, <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code</a>, how to get involved in the community.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Google Summer of Code | Coding Period | Week 9</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-9/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-9/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-9-cover.png" alt=""></p>
<p>This week — July 9 to July 15— was the fourth week of the coding period of <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code (GSoC)</a> with <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a>. If you want to know more about this you can read the <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc/intro-to-google-summer-of-code-with-systers-open-source-dbdaa92bd189">introduction to my journey</a>, <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc">my latest weekly blog posts</a> or <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/wiki/GSoC-2018-Isabel-Costa#weekly-status-report-for-week-9">my weekly status report</a> for this week.</p>
<p>I focused a lot of time developing the UI prototype for the Android application, which I’ll explain in the end. Apart from this, I did other types of tasks.</p>
<h3>Project management tasks</h3>
<p>I had a 1:1 with my mentor, <a href="https://github.com/Dilu9218">Dilushi</a>, to agree on how to create issues regarding Quality Assurance and how to approach this. We thought about how to spread the word about contributing to the project through manual testing, how to present to the community tasks that do not involve coding but involve testing the backend and can be worked by multiple contributors who wish to test multiple test cases and report bugs. So we created the <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/issues/86">first issue #86</a> that shows a few test cases that contributors can follow to do their testing and has a link to the <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1kStdMWK9K93zlsjIFbU2fODE98NK3a4nJGtYtBEyrlo/">Quality Assurance Google Docs I created last week</a>.</p>
<h3>Development tasks</h3>
<p>My mentor, <a href="https://github.com/m-murad">Murad</a>, shared a blog post to help me configure the backend to be able to connect with a remote MySQL database from <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/rds/">Amazon Relational Database Service (RDS)</a>.<br>
This post, <a href="https://medium.com/@rodkey/deploying-a-flask-application-on-aws-a72daba6bb80">“Deploying a Flask application on AWS”</a>, is very descriptive and showed me how simple it was to use another type of URI to use other types of databases. For this, I submitted <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/89">pull request #89</a>.</p>
<p>I also fixed a bug reported by a first-time contributor of Mentorship System, <a href="https://github.com/bethanyr">Bethany Rentz</a>, while doing manual testing. Here’s the bug report <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/issues/83">issue #83</a>.</p>
<h3>Project Weekly Meeting</h3>
<p>In this week’s meeting, I shared my proposal for the Android application features for 3rd coding phase. Basically, I divided into 3 major stories: User, Mentorship Relation, and Tasks. This was my proposal of main feature stories:</p>
<ul>
<li>Week 10: User arc;</li>
<li>Week 11: Mentorship Relation arc;</li>
<li>Week 12: Tasks arc;</li>
<li>Week 13: buffer week to complete unfinished tasks and fix any critical bug.</li>
</ul>
<p>As a reminder in this system, we have users that have 1:1 mentorship relations with each other, where one is the mentor and the other is the mentee. The mentorship relations can have tasks associated, created by the mentor or the mentee.</p>
<p>Other important decisions done during the meeting was how the Android application was going to be developed. We agreed on using Kotlin to develop the Android application. This was a major doubt of mine since all the Android applications are developed in Java, I didn’t know if the community wanted to stick with Java. My mentors and project manager agreed on using kotlin since my mentors were comfortable and open to this approach and this would add a new skill set to the community, where other contributors could learn and contribute using kotlin. This is also a possibility because I’ve used kotlin before, both in work and side projects, so I can use it now without having to learn it from scratch. We also agreed on using <a href="https://8thlight.com/blog/uncle-bob/2012/08/13/the-clean-architecture.html">Clean Architecture</a>. This was an architecture I’ve heard before but never applied to a project. I’m excited to learn more about this and Android architecture components I never used before.</p>
<h3>UI Prototype Design tasks</h3>
<p>This week I looked into Material Design to design the UI prototype of high fidelity for the Mentorship System so that I can follow it while developing the Android application. For this, I created the very first issue of the systers/mentorship-android repository, <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-android/issues/1">issue #1</a>.</p>
<p>I used JustInMind prototyping tool, which is very intuitive and easy to use. Here’s the <a href="https://www.justinmind.com/usernote/tests/35756605/35766303/35777319/index.html">public link for the UI prototype</a>, this is being actively improved with community’s feedback.</p>
<p>The latest screens I designed were the Tasks feature screen. I intend to write a post regarding the design of the UI prototype of Mentorship System. Here’s an image of these screens and a comparison with the before and what I propose for this feature. I already shared this with the community, now I’m waiting for some feedback until the next project weekly meeting.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.justinmind.com/usernote/tests/35756605/35766303/35777319/index.html" title="https://www.justinmind.com/usernote/tests/35756605/35766303/35777319/index.html"><strong>MSPrototype</strong><br>
_Generated by Justinmind on Fri Jul 20 21:51:28 UTC 2018_www.justinmind.com</a><a href="https://www.justinmind.com/usernote/tests/35756605/35766303/35777319/index.html"></a></p>
<p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-9-ui-design.png" alt="UI Redesign of Tasks feature"></p>
<h3>Open Source community tasks</h3>
<p>This week I started hosting Ask Me Anything (AMA) sessions dedicated to newcomers, where I would be available in a <a href="https://hangouts.google.com">Google Hangout</a> call to answer any questions newcomers might have about how to start contributing, how I got into open source, my google summer of code experience and how to participate in Open Source. I came to <a href="http://systers.io/">Systers Open Source</a> community in March this year, so I was a newcomer before. I know that sometimes it can be very intimidating speaking out in the open on Slack in front of the whole community. So I wanted to show newcomers that this is just intimidating in the beginning and it sure can be confusing but it does not have to be like that.</p>
<p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-9-ama.png" alt="First announcement about my Ask Me Anything (AMA) sessions"></p>
<h3>Plans for next week</h3>
<ul>
<li>Host more AMA sessions;</li>
<li>Fix bugs and merge conflicts from new pull requests from Backend;</li>
<li>Start implementing in Kotlin the User arc feature;</li>
<li>Create more issues for newcomers and first-time contributors for the Mentorship System to contribute.</li>
</ul>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Google Summer of Code | Coding Period | Week 8</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-8/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-8/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-8-cover.png" alt=""></p>
<p>This week — July 2 to July 8— was the fourth week of the coding period of <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code (GSoC)</a> with <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a>. If you want to know more about this you can read the <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc/intro-to-google-summer-of-code-with-systers-open-source-dbdaa92bd189">introduction to my journey</a>, <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc">my latest weekly blog posts</a> or <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/wiki/GSoC-2018-Isabel-Costa#weekly-status-report-for-week-8">my weekly status report</a> for this week.</p>
<h3>Non-coding tasks</h3>
<p>I asked for the “<a href="https://medium.com/systers-opensource/mentorship-system-by-systers-52dbe1275d9f">Mentorship System by Systers</a>” to be published on <a href="https://medium.com/systers-opensource">Systers Open Source medium publication</a>, after waiting for some feedback from the community.</p>
<p>I <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1dcnb1GQXR7LPiknADsbNY9b0kTKY2dZt3WSfED4ntfU/edit?usp=sharing">presented the Mentorship System Backend</a> to the community and <a href="http://systers-mentorship-dev.eu-central-1.elasticbeanstalk.com/">opened it for testing</a>. I presented with the purpose not only to show my work to the community but to explain how to test the system. After presenting in the Community Open Session, I also announced in relevant channels of <a href="http://systers.io/slack-systers-opensource/">Systers Open Source slack</a> that anyone could start testing the <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">backend</a> (anyone including newcomers and other contributors). I showed how someone could test the backend using <a href="https://swagger.io/">Swagger</a> UI and <a href="https://www.getpostman.com/">Postman</a>, the constraints and test case examples.</p>
<p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-8-presentation.png" alt="Slides from the Backend demo presentation"></p>
<p>Aside from the presentation I also created a <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1kStdMWK9K93zlsjIFbU2fODE98NK3a4nJGtYtBEyrlo/edit?usp=sharing">Google Docs regarding Quality Assurance</a>, to help guide contributors that want to help test testing the system. I documented test cases where the outcome is either a success or a failure. Here’s an example of a group of tests cases for accepting a mentorship request feature.</p>
<p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-8-test-case-doc.png" alt="Excerpt from the Quality Assurance Google Docs with test case for accepting a request feature"></p>
<p>This week I started looking into <a href="https://material.io/design/">Material Design</a> to develop a more high fidelity wireframe than the first one I did in the Community Bonding period. I also thought about the minimum features of the future mobile app, to get done until the end of the GSoC coding period (in 5 weeks).</p>
<h3>Coding tasks</h3>
<p>I submitted a <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/75">PR #75</a> to restrict GET /users API to authenticated users. This endpoint was very useful while testing the <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">backend</a> during its development, but for a complete feature, this endpoint has to be restricted so that only users of this system can see other users profiles and they can only see public data (defined by the user being displayed).</p>
<p>The task that took me more time of the week was implementing a cron job to complete a mentorship relation. I ended up creating a cron background scheduler using <a href="https://apscheduler.readthedocs.io">apscheduler</a> library. With the cron job I scheduled a function to run every day at 23h59. This is needed to complete mentorship relations which are passed their end date. For this, I submitted <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/79">PR #79</a>.</p>
<p>I also searched a lot to debug an issue we were having with the deployed server. The Authorization header wasn’t being received in the server side. I didn’t know where this issue was coming from, first I thought it was from <a href="https://github.com/vimalloc/flask-jwt-extended">flask-jwt-extended</a>, then after a lot of research, I noticed that we needed to <a href="http://modwsgi.readthedocs.io/en/develop/configuration-directives/WSGIPassAuthorization.html">configure Apache to pass the Authorization headers to the WSGI application</a>, our flask app. Enabling passing of authorization headers meant setting the WSGIPassAuthorization directive to On value. To solve this issue, I worked with one of my mentors, <a href="https://github.com/m-murad">Murad</a>, that dealt with the server deployment and helped me a lot to have the <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">backend</a> ready for testing.</p>
<h3>Plans for the next week</h3>
<ul>
<li>Have a wireframe to follow while developing the Android application;</li>
<li>Test extensively the backend and create bug reporting issues (if needed);</li>
<li>Fix bugs found while testing the backend;</li>
<li>Start the base of the Android application.</li>
</ul>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Introducing Mentorship System</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/introducing-mentorship-system/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/introducing-mentorship-system/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/mentorship-system-initial-logo.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Mentorship System is an open source project I proposed for <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code</a> 2018 with <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a>, where women mentor each other for a certain period of time on career development topics. A support system for women to advance their careers and count on each other.</p>
<h3>Motivation</h3>
<p>In my first year of college, I had a mentor, that helped me get past the blocker of not getting python in the first classes. It made me feel that I wasn’t alone on not being able to grasp programming at first.</p>
<p>I was a student mentor in my 2nd and 3rd year of college and I met some awesome first-year students which I’m still in contact these days. I found very rewarding of passing on the knowledge that I’ve been gathering through my college years. The idea of helping others with the knowledge that already took me some time to gather fascinates me. There are a lot of things I learned during my journey of navigating the Tech industry that I would like to have learned sooner. But it’s never too late.</p>
<p>I know about some women that are interested in switching careers to Tech, and whenever I get to talk to them I try to help them understand how to begin in this industry and some of the steps to take. I’m also giving advice from time to time to a woman I found on Women Who Code slack that is currently in the process of changing to the tech industry and some other friends.</p>
<p>Having said this I’ve seen benefits of helping others and being helped. We can all learn from others’ experiences and retribute with our knowledge by helping others. I feel that we can also benefit by lifting each other up by having a support system, i.e., having someone that we can feel comfortable with asking questions and getting feedback on our progress for a certain goal we may have.</p>
<p><img src="/images/woc-in-tech-chat-4.jpeg" alt="Photo credits go to wocintechchat.com: https://www.flickr.com/photos/wocintechchat/"></p>
<p><em>Photo credits go to wocintechchat.com: <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/wocintechchat/">https://www.flickr.com/photos/wocintechchat/</a></em></p>
<h3>The Mentorship System</h3>
<p>So the idea consists of a mobile application that matches women to help and support one or both parties. One is the mentor that will be a support/accountability buddy and/or give advice to a woman that wants mentorship, for a period of time established by both parties. Some basic features will be:</p>
<ul>
<li>A mentorship relation will be between two users only, where both could focus on the mentee’s career development goals;</li>
<li>Schedule meetings between the mentor and mentee, to agree on each others commitments to the relationship;</li>
<li>Tasks assigned to the mentee, which when completed become achievements of this mentorship relation;</li>
<li>Mentorship agreements were both agree on the time period, the topic of mentorship and who’s the mentor and mentee of the relation.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Who are the target users?</h4>
<p>Women who are already in the STEM industry (mentors) would volunteer some time, at their discretion, to help other women (mentees) who are new to this industry or are already in it but need some sort of mentorship.</p>
<p>This would not focus only on students, this would target women from any age, background, work in tech experience, and so on. E.g.: a good example would be women switching careers, maybe self-taught — not currently enrolled in any specific educational program.</p>
<p>Mentors don’t need to be experts they can be students helping older women who are switching careers and can help in some way. One criteria used may be the match of fields and/or technologies used between the mentor and mentee.</p>
<h4>What are the things mentors can help mentees with?</h4>
<p>Topics where mentors could guide, are not restricted to technical advice, it’s about more than that: how to navigate the industry or a certain area of it; public speaking; online presence; blogging; side projects; open source; GitHub; interviews; negotiation; CVs/Resumes reviews; how to use Twitter and LinkedIn; how to deal with burnout.</p>
<h4>What are the benefits for the users?</h4>
<p>This is supposed to be a safe place for women to lift each other up, become more confident in themselves while being supported by other women while they achieve something important for them and their careers.</p>
<p>Women in tech could get to meet other women in tech. This app could create bonding opportunities between the mentor and mentee. It can help empower women and help in discovering ways to evolve their careers through knowledge sharing.</p>
<p>By helping women navigate within the industry, and make sure they’re not alone we can help women keep having interest in technology and therefore being involved in it.</p>
<p><img src="/images/woc-in-tech-chat-5.jpeg" alt="Photo credits go to wocintechchat.com: https://www.flickr.com/photos/wocintechchat/"></p>
<p><em>Photo credits go to wocintechchat.com: <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/wocintechchat/">https://www.flickr.com/photos/wocintechchat/</a></em></p>
<h3>What makes this better than other solutions?</h3>
<p>Most of the apps I’ve seen are either targeted to students and/or companies, are paid apps or are focused on technical content. I think that Mentorship System would be great since it would not have these constraints.</p>
<p>It is based on the foundations of volunteerism. By being open source everyone can collaborate add features, ideas and help to maintain the app.</p>
<p>This isn’t targeted to a specific demographic among women, this would help anyone from any age, background and from any stage of their career.</p>
<p>This is also a free option for people in need of mentoring, and can’t afford other paid options. The mentorship relation does not need to be focused on tech-related aspects of a career, this would be used with regards to everything related to having a career in Tech.</p>
<h3>Finding more about the project</h3>
<p>The <strong>Mentorship System is under active development</strong> on <a href="https://github.com">GitHub</a>, so the features and data model proposed initially might change since the proposal submission. In case you want to follow the development here are some resources:</p>
<ul>
<li>GitHub repositories: <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">systers/mentorship-backend</a> and <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-android">systers/mentorship-android</a></li>
<li>Join <a href="http://systers.io/slack-systers-opensource/">Systers Open Source slack</a>. We discuss this project in #mentorship-system channel.</li>
</ul>
<p>You can find more about this project requirements and ideas:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1TkyLWbVyW9WHEoqFBwpE1GE6vDRf7aoITT6i7tBFKsw">Initial Google Summer of Code proposal</a>;</li>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1cMqzZbbvgAzi54SYBdxNL9vg2y-0aJikCbkfwZYouUg">Initial pitch presentation slides presented in the Community Open Session</a>;</li>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1RhYMjyd1yhAWarO7spRWOYm-KNgFsO9rNgO6ssnEC-o">Application features documentation</a> (live document);</li>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1qDTJK-ItAaek5ZBSLd4i8ShxLDcU5D2b4ZdIBTNxEJM">Backend documentation</a> (live document).</li>
</ul>
<p>Remember that this <strong>project is being developed open source</strong>, so if you have ideas and want to participate in this project development <strong>feel free to reach us</strong> on slack to contribute with feedback, ideas, or check if there are any issues you can help with. We welcome contributors from any background!</p>
<p><img src="/images/ms-anitab-org-bar.png" alt=""></p>
<p>Thank you for reading this post!</p>
<p>You can follow <a href="https://medium.com/systers-opensource">Systers Open Source Medium publication</a> to know updates from the community!</p>
<p>Check out <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source projects on GitHub</a> and find more about the <a href="http://systers.io/">Systers Open Source community</a>.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Google Summer of Code | Coding Period | Week 7</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-7/"/>
    <updated>2018-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-7/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-7-cover.png" alt=""></p>
<p>This week — June 25 to July 1— was the fourth week of the coding period of <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code (GSoC)</a> with <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a>. If you want to know more about this you can read the <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc/intro-to-google-summer-of-code-with-systers-open-source-dbdaa92bd189">introduction to my journey</a>, <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc">my latest weekly blog posts</a> or <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/wiki/GSoC-2018-Isabel-Costa#weekly-status-report-for-week-7">my weekly status report</a> for this week.</p>
<h3>Non-technical work</h3>
<p>This week, my mentor <a href="https://github.com/m-murad">Murad</a>, deployed the <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">backend</a>, I’m working on, to <a href="https://aws.amazon.com">Amazon Web Services (AWS)</a>. So this can already be used by community members without the need to run the project and test it locally. So I started the presentation slides to do a demo of the <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">Mentorship System backend</a> and test it in front of community members. I also want to encourage the community to test the backend API intensively through the Swagger UI to receive feedback and detect potential bugs.</p>
<p>On Thursday, I wrote a blog post about Mentorship System, presenting the idea and the motivation behind this project I proposed for GSoC. After writing it I shared with the community to receive feedback before publishing it and then I submitted to <a href="https://medium.com/systers-opensource">Systers Open Source medium’s publication</a>.</p>
<h3>Technical work</h3>
<p>I’ll explain some features of the application and backend already discussed and their implementation.</p>
<h4>Delete/Reject/Cancel a mentorship relation or request APIs</h4>
<p>In the Mentorship System, we have users that can both be a mentor or a mentee in a 1:1 relationship. In this mentorship relation, we’ll have a user that takes the action to send a mentorship request to another user.</p>
<p><strong>Delete a mentorship request</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Feature:</strong> A user that sends the request should be able to delete this, once the user is no longer interested in having a mentorship relation with the other user.</li>
<li><strong>Implementation:</strong> Submit <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/73">PR #73</a> with the API implementation to delete a mentorship request. For this, I created <code>DELETE /mentorship_relation/{id}</code> API and developed the tests. Only the user that sends the request can delete this request.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Reject a mentorship request</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Feature:</strong> The user that receives a mentorship request should be able to reject a mentorship request if this user is not interested in it.</li>
<li><strong>Implementation:</strong> Submitted <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/62">PR #62</a> with the API implementation to reject a mentorship request. For this, I created <code>PUT /mentorship_relation/{id}/reject</code> API. This API is also restricted to authenticated users. Only the receiver of the request can reject this.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cancel a mentorship relation</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Feature:</strong> During a mentorship relation, both the mentor and the mentee should be able to cancel the relation if this is no longer working for the users involved.</li>
<li><strong>Implementation:</strong> Submitted <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/61">PR #61</a> with the API implementation to cancel a mentorship request. For this, I created <code>PUT /mentorship_relation/{id}/cancel</code> API, developed the DAO function to interact with the database and implemented tests for this. The API is restricted for authenticated users. Both of the users involved in the mentorship relation can cancel it.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Get all mentorship relations and requests</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Feature:</strong> The users should be able to check the pending, previous, and current requests.</li>
<li><strong>Implementation:</strong> Submitted <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/74">PR #74</a> with the API implementation to get all mentorship requests or relations. This is still being reviewed so the endpoints aren’t confirmed yet. Although, we already discussed the logic of this feature: pending requests are requests which weren’t accepted by the receiver and the end date of the relation has not passed yet; the current mentorship relation is the only relation which is currently accepted by the receiver of the request, so it’s ongoing; The previous mentorship relations are defined as having an end date passed the current date.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-7-swagger.png" alt="Snippet of the Swagger Documentation on Mentorship System API"></p>
<h4>Using flask-jwt-extended instead of flask-jwt</h4>
<p>I replaced the usage of <a href="https://github.com/mattupstate/flask-jwt">flask-jwt</a> for <a href="https://github.com/vimalloc/flask-jwt-extended">flask-jwt-extended</a> which provided me with more flexibility to define my error messages depending on the exceptions thrown on the backend (e.g.: error for invalid or expired authentication token). This new extension also provided me with flexibility on the checks performed on POST /login API. This library also appears to be actively maintained. For this I submitted <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/64">PR #64</a>.</p>
<h4>Background scheduler to complete mentorship relation</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Feature:</strong> A mentorship relation is defined within a period of time, with a start and end date. A relation which was accepted by the receiver of the request and is ongoing ends in the end date defined for the relation.</li>
<li><strong>Implementation:</strong> I’m implementing a background scheduler (cron job) using <a href="https://github.com/agronholm/apscheduler">apscheduler library</a> to check every day for mentorship relations in the <code>ACCEPTED</code> state which the end date has passed the current date, and marks it as with the <code>COMPLETED</code> state. This is still in progress because I have yet to test this.</li>
</ul>
<h4>Email verification feature final retouch</h4>
<p>I implemented some changes to the previously sent <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/53">PR #53</a>. The changes include improvements on the email template (according to the project weekly feedback), a new endpoint for a user to be able to resend a confirmation token to its email and allowing only users with the email confirmed to login into the app.</p>
<p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-7-conf-email.png" alt="2nd version of the email template for email confirmation"></p>
<h4>Export Swagger documentation and Postman collection in json format</h4>
<p>I’ve been studying a way to export the <a href="https://www.getpostman.com/">postman</a> and <a href="https://swagger.io/">swagger</a> collection, without having to manually download the swagger json file or set up a postman collection manually. I already started developing following the flask-restplus documentation on both <a href="https://flask-restplus.readthedocs.io/en/stable/postman.html">postman</a> and <a href="https://flask-restplus.readthedocs.io/en/stable/swagger.html">swagger</a> exporting.</p>
<h3>Plans for next week</h3>
<ul>
<li>Present to the community what I have from the Mentorship System Backend;</li>
<li>Finish the cron job to complete a mentorship relation;</li>
<li>Have this week’s PRs merged;</li>
<li>Discuss mobile application development!</li>
</ul>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Google Summer of Code | Coding Period | Week 6</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-6/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-6/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-6-cover.png" alt=""></p>
<p>This week — June 18 to June 24 — was the fourth week of the coding period of <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code (GSoC)</a> with <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a>. If you want to know more about this you can read the <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc/intro-to-google-summer-of-code-with-systers-open-source-dbdaa92bd189">introduction to my journey</a> , <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc">my latest weekly blog posts</a> or <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/wiki/GSoC-2018-Isabel-Costa#weekly-status-report-for-week-6">my weekly status report</a> for this week.</p>
<p>I’ll start with a shout out to <a href="http://systers.io/">Systers</a> organization and then speak about the technical issues I tackled this week.</p>
<h3>Shout-out to Systers</h3>
<p><a href="http://systers.io/">Systers community</a> is really welcoming and caring about their students. One of the things that I really like is time and energy investment they do to help students in career development. One example from this week was a session scheduled to help GSoC students review or create their CV/Resume. They did this because there was some demand for CV/Resume reviews. The session was initially divided into 2 parallel sessions with different targets (e.g.: some needed a resume targeted for a specific job/scholarship opportunity and other needed just to review existing CVs). These sessions were joined later. Admins helped us reviewing the resumes, but I want to highlight <a href="https://medium.com/u/5a131e8c1c06">Ramit Sawhney</a>, one of this year’s GSoC mentor, that was present for about 3 hours giving extensive tips and reviewing resumes one by one, from at least 9 students.</p>
<h3>Development tasks</h3>
<p>These are some of the technical tasks I was involved with. I’ve been developing in the <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/tree/gsoc18-code">gsoc18-code branch</a> of <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">systers/mentorship-backend</a> repository.</p>
<h4>Support for environment variables</h4>
<p>One task I accomplished this week was to add support to read environment variables (<a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/51">PR #51</a>). In order to avoid disclosing sensitive data and push it into the git repository, the app needed to have support to environment variables. In this way sensitive data such as a SECRET_KEY can be exported with:</p>
<pre><code>export SECRET_KEY=&lt;app-secret-key&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>And later imported within the app like this:</p>
<pre><code>import os

(…)

secret_key = os.getenv(‘SECRET_KEY’)

(…)
</code></pre>
<p>This support is also very helpful for the email verification feature since we also need to use credentials from an email account to send the emails on behalf of the Mentorship System.</p>
<h4>Email Verification</h4>
<p>Speaking of email verification, this is almost done. This week I cleared some doubts I had about this feature so that I could complete it. I have already the email being sent to the newly registered user. I already have <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/53">PR #53</a> with most of the work done. Here’s the first version of the email being sent, which will be updated according to this week’s feedback.</p>
<p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-6-email-conf.png" alt="1º version of the email template"></p>
<p>I mentioned <a href="https://realpython.com/handling-email-confirmation-in-flask/">“Handling email confirmation in Flask”</a> blog post in a previous post, but I haven’t used it until this week. This post was critical to speed up my development on the email verification feature. This post is packed with the basics that I needed to make the functionality work, from generating the unique token to verify the email, to the email template rendering to be sent via email. This is also possible because of the <a href="https://pythonhosted.org/Flask-Mail/">Flask-Mail</a> extension.</p>
<h4>Revoke admin user role</h4>
<p>The issue to revoke an admin role was in the product backlog for some time but with lower priority. Because I was waiting on other PRs to be merged so that I could move on with mentorship relation feature, I started cleaning up some issues, such as this one to revoke an admin role from a user. I also cleared some doubts about this in the project weekly meeting, so that I could have the PR with the correct business logic. I submitted <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/54">PR #54</a> for this.</p>
<h4>Accept mentorship request API</h4>
<p>This weekend I finally finished one very important feature, accepting a mentorship relation request. This feature took some time to understand according to the database model and to establish the constraints and logic. I developed this and did some tests to ensure that the business logic was respected. I submitted <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/58">PR #58</a> for this.</p>
<h4>Applying application factory pattern</h4>
<p>One problem I was facing was that I couldn’t get the tests for the API services to work. I was just able to test other modules of the flask application, as the database models and the data access objects (DAOs). I wasn’t able to simulate requests to the API. I have been looking into this problem from time to time but giving it less priority. This week I finally tackled this. I already had a feeling that this had something to do with the app’s structure. The problem was with the initialization of the flask application object and its extensions. These flask extensions were not initialized with the app together. When getting the application object in the tests, the application would come without the extensions initialized. So I tried out a design pattern, application factory pattern, which is recommended in the flask website <a href="http://flask.pocoo.org/docs/1.0/patterns/appfactories/">here</a>. Finally, I got this to work by creating as recommended a function create_app() that would return the application with all the extensions lazily initialized. I submitted <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/57">PR #57</a> for this issue.</p>
<h3>Plans for next week</h3>
<ul>
<li>One of the things that I started studying was the possibility to export automatically the swagger and postman collection through the <a href="http://flask-restplus.readthedocs.io/">flask-RESTPlus</a> extension that helps to document the API with specific annotations;</li>
<li>Once the PR regarding the application factory pattern, get merged do more tests to cover the REST API;</li>
<li>Implement API to reject/cancel/complete a mentorship relation;</li>
<li>Present the <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">backend</a> in the Community Open Session;</li>
<li>Open the <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">backend</a> for the community to test it.</li>
</ul>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Google Summer of Code | Coding Period | Week 5</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-5/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-5/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-5-cover.png" alt="gsoc and systers logos"></p>
<p>This week — June 11 to June 17— was the fourth week of the coding period of <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code (GSoC)</a> with <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a>. If you want to know more about this you can read the <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc/intro-to-google-summer-of-code-with-systers-open-source-dbdaa92bd189">introduction to my journey</a> , <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc">my latest weekly blog posts</a> or <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/wiki/GSoC-2018-Isabel-Costa#weekly-status-report-for-week-5">my weekly status report</a> for this week.</p>
<h2>Reviewing database model design</h2>
<p>I started the week with questions regarding the data model and the logic behind the mentorship feature. So in a 1:1 meeting with <a href="https://github.com/Dilu9218">Dilushi</a> I tried to clarify these doubts. One thing <a href="https://github.com/Dilu9218">Dilushi</a> taught me this week was that when designing systems, with similar features to existing systems, we can take a look at them and learn from them since these have already passed through the thought process for the feature we’re analyzing. This reminds me of a saying, that most of the times we don’t have to reinvent the wheel. Also, this helps us designing a good database model, which is important since future feature development will depend on this. From this meeting, we observed that a mentorship relation request is similar to a friendship/connection request on Facebook/LinkedIn, although it has its differences.</p>
<p>I started implementing a part of the API and data model, related to the mentorship relation feature. In a POST request body data for a mentorship request, I was expecting the IDs of the mentor and mentee, as well of the sender and receiver of the request. My mentors had already advised me that having both sender and receiver user ID, might not be necessary. In the 1:1 meeting, we found a blog post that presented “<a href="https://www.9lessons.info/2014/03/facebook-style-friend-request-system.html">Facebook Style Friend Request System Database Design</a>”, which helped me understand we only needed one field to know who was the sender and the receiver. This field would represent just the sender, the one user that took the action to send a request. Because mentor and mentee ID have to be the same as the sender and receiver of the request, we could infer the receiver just by knowing the sender user.</p>
<p>After this meeting I started researching about database design and normalization, to optimize the data model scheme. I was refreshing my memory from what I learned before in database course in college. So I found a <a href="https://udacity.com">Udacity</a> online course to help me understand more about this topic. I watched some videos that I found relevant from the “<a href="https://eu.udacity.com/course/database-systems-concepts-design--ud150">Database Systems Concepts &amp; Design</a>” online course.</p>
<p>Another resource I found very helpful was a video called “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UDFRhj_K508">How to do Database Normalization</a>” on YouTube. This really helped me understand about the trade-off of flexibility and performance of normalization of database models, and when this normalization is needed or not. I started to see some potential areas for normalization in our current data model. So I was ready to discuss this in the project weekly.</p>
<h2>Importance of having a MVP</h2>
<p>In the project weekly, I was about to discuss some potential areas for improvements and doubts about some features when my mentor <a href="https://github.com/m-murad">Murad</a> thought me another lesson. I was trying to a very good data model and the complex features already established and to be implemented. <a href="https://github.com/m-murad">Murad</a> showed me that for a first-time project it’s important to have first an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minimum_viable_product">minimum viable product (MVP)</a>, and then improve upon receiving feedback from the community and its users. This also refers to an Agile development methodology, that I’m still learning and adjusting to. We’ll develop product deliverables, with minimum features that can be used by our target users, and then improve this in every development sprint. This led us to simplify a lot of the features, in a way that would not compromise the database design already defined and knowing that this could be later improved (e.g.: with database migrations). These simplifications helped me set realistic goals for the Mentorship System development during GSoC.</p>
<p>Some of the simplified features are:</p>
<ul>
<li>When a User sends a request, this will not be editable by the receiving user;</li>
<li>When a User accepts a request, the mentorship relation starts automatically, and both users cannot receive requests during the accepted relation.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Completed tasks</h2>
<p>I dedicated this week to implement the API for mentorship relation feature, regarding sending a mentorship request between two users and listing all of these requests. I submitted <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/47">PR #47</a>. In this PR I fixed the Mentorship data model, did tests for the new API and fixed other tests.</p>
<h2>Plans for next week</h2>
<p>I plan to finish the mentorship relation feature API. This includes the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Handling the following states: pending (sender awaits receiver’s response); accept (from the receiver to the sender); reject (from the receiver to the sender); cancel (from sender or receiver during a mentorship relation); completed;</li>
<li>I’ll take a look into how to develop a cron job to set the mentorship relation into the complete state after the end date passes;</li>
<li>Finish email verification feature.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Lessons learned</h2>
<ul>
<li>When doing something that might resemble a common feature in other existing systems, we can learn from these that already went through a thought process;</li>
<li>It is important to have first a minimum viable product, instead of doing all the complex features in the first version of an app. We can start with an MVP and then improve a product after receiving feedback from users.</li>
</ul>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Google Summer of Code | Coding Period | Week 4</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-4/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-4/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-4-cover.png" alt="systers logo with gsoc logo"></p>
<p>This week — June 4 to June 10— was the fourth week of the coding period of <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code (GSoC)</a> with <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a>. If you want to know more about this you can read the <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc/intro-to-google-summer-of-code-with-systers-open-source-dbdaa92bd189">introduction to my journey</a> , <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc">my latest weekly blog posts</a> or <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/wiki/GSoC-2018-Isabel-Costa#weekly-status-report-for-week-4">my weekly status report</a> for this week.</p>
<p>This week I dedicated a lot of my time preparing for my thesis presentation, on June 7th. So I had to manage better my time to produce work for GSoC and still have a good preparation for my thesis. Now that I presented the thesis I can dedicate much more time for GSoC.</p>
<h2>Time and work management</h2>
<p>Even with an intense thesis preparation I still managed to submit some PRs for small tasks, mostly bugs, at the beginning of this week. I understand that it is very important to be present and reachable when working remote. So I responded to all code reviews within 24 hours and stayed active on Slack, communicating with the community and my mentors. Also, it is important to keep the community informed of my workload, so I made sure to keep the <a href="https://calendar.google.com/">Google Calendar</a> for my project updated with my limited availability and other commitments (related to my thesis).</p>
<p>An interesting thing I noticed this week is how the scrum check-ins help me keep accountable. Scrum check-ins are short messages we, GSoC students, have to post on <a href="https://slack.com/">Slack</a> every Monday, Wednesday, and Friday of each week at 5 pm GMT+1 timezone. This helps me show that although I might be working more on the thesis, I’m still responsive and doing GSoC related work. One thing that helps me deliver these check-ins in time is to start writing or at least preparing the template for the next check-in, after the latest check-in, instead of doing this very near to the deadline.</p>
<p>I attended the project weekly meeting and discussed the mentorship relation feature. Since the First Coding Phase ends this week, I wanted to optimize the time to finish or at least start working on the most important feature of the Mentorship System, the mentorship relations. So I suggested to my mentors that we could re-prioritized the issues planned for this phase, giving priority to mentorship relation feature. After this re-prioritization, we reviewed the mentorship relation feature, the first fields I could work with and the APIs I could start developing.</p>
<h2>Completed tasks</h2>
<p>One thing I really like to do is to organize issues, create them, adding labels and descriptive descriptions. This week I created more issues and broke some features into smaller issues, to keep the pull requests very focused on one small task and keep all organized.</p>
<p>Here’s a summary of this week’s completed action items:</p>
<ul>
<li>I solved bugs found the week before and responded to code review change requests — PRs <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/33">#33</a>, <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/34">#34</a>, <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/35">#35</a>;</li>
<li>I developed the Mentorship Relation database model, which will serve as the base for the APIs regarding the mentorship relation feature. The APIs include sending a mentorship request, accepting or rejecting a mentorship relation, and canceling a request — <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/41">PR #41</a>;</li>
<li>Created tests for app configurations — <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/issues/37">PR #37</a>;</li>
<li>I changed the Login API response to return the expiry UNIX timestamp along with the access token —<a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/44">PR #44</a>;</li>
<li>Created a function to validate the email regex — <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/45">PR#45</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Presenting my work</h2>
<p>This week the GSoC Happy Hour focused on showing off students’ work. GSoC Happy Hour is about spending some time getting to know fellow GSoC students and mentors. The latest ones have been focused on playing games together. This time, I got to demo the backend API I’ve been developing these last 4 weeks, and use the <a href="https://swagger.io/tools/swagger-ui/">Swagger UI</a> to present the API functionalities. This was the first time I’ve demo this to someone (besides my mentors), and it was slightly intimidating but a good thing since other could see my work. I got to see other students work, as well, which helped me broaden my view of what others are doing and have an overview of what technologies are being used for the other projects.</p>
<h2>Shout-outs for blog posts</h2>
<p>I spent an afternoon searching for a way to define the data model. The challenge of this was that Mentorship Relation is a relation between 2 instances of the same User data model. I researched about what type of relationship this would be (e.g.: many to many or one to many). To develop the Mentorship Relation database model I followed this blog post, <a href="https://www.codementor.io/sheena/understanding-sqlalchemy-cheat-sheet-du107lawl">A SQLAlchemy Cheat Sheet</a> by <a href="https://www.codementor.io/sheena">Sheena</a>. The section that saved my day was “Multiple relationships with the same table”.</p>
<p>Another blog post that really helped me was <a href="http://blog.tecladocode.com/learn-python-advanced-configuration-of-flask-jwt/">“Advanced configuration of Flask-JWT”</a> by <a href="https://twitter.com/tecladocode">Jose Salvatierra</a>. This helped me with getting the expiry UNIX timestamp for a <a href="https://jwt.io/">JWT</a> access token, using the <a href="https://pythonhosted.org/Flask-JWT/">flask-jwt</a> extension. What also helped me was looking at the <a href="https://github.com/mattupstate/flask-jwt/blob/master/flask_jwt/__init__.py">source code of this extension</a>. I wanted the expiry token to be sent along with the access token in the Login API response, thereby solving <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/issues/39">issue #39</a>.</p>
<h2>Plans for next week</h2>
<ul>
<li>I already started working on the email verification feature while waiting for the mentorship relation data model PR to be merged.</li>
<li>When this PR is merged, I’ll start working on the Mentorship Relation feature API. I plan to finish this API next week and do a demo in the Community Open Session, to present to the community the progress of the backend API.</li>
</ul>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Google Summer of Code | Coding Period | Week 3</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-3/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-3/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-3-cover.png" alt=""></p>
<p>This week — May 28 to June 3 — was the third week of the coding period of <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code (GSoC)</a> with <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a>. If you want to know more about this you can read the <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc/intro-to-google-summer-of-code-with-systers-open-source-dbdaa92bd189">introduction to my journey</a> , <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc">my latest weekly blog posts</a> or <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/wiki/GSoC-2018-Isabel-Costa#weekly-status-report-for-week-3">my weekly status report</a> for this week.</p>
<p>These first weeks, I’ve been balancing GSoC and my Master’s thesis work. Next week I’ll present my dissertation and then I can fully focus on GSoC work. Even with the thesis I still managed to get some work done.</p>
<p>This week I had these 3 pull requests (PR) merged:</p>
<ul>
<li>Add Swagger documentation for Login API <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/20">#20</a>;</li>
<li>Add initial tests that cover the majority of database models and data access object (DAO) <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/16">#16</a>;</li>
<li>Update pull request template, to have checklist items to update swagger and postman JSON files. These files must be updated every time someone updates the API functionalities <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/27">#27</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>I also created <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/issues?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;q=is%3Aissue+created%3A2018-05-28..2018-06-03+author%3Aisabelcosta">some issues on GitHub and organized them</a> on the <a href="https://www.zenhub.com/">ZenHub</a> board. In case you’re unfamiliar with <a href="https://www.zenhub.com/">ZenHub</a>, this is an agile project management tool for <a href="https://github.com">GitHub</a>. Some of these issues were based on bugs found by one of my mentors, <a href="https://github.com/m-murad">Murad</a>, and other issues were discussed at this week’s project meeting.</p>
<h3>Challenges</h3>
<p>This week I had to squash commits on multiple occasions. For <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/14">my first PR</a>, I had to squash some commits of a branch, which did not include the most recent commit (<a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/24310554/how-do-i-squash-specific-commits-on-a-local-branch/24310701#24310701">here’s a stack overflow answer that helped me</a>). For some of my next PRs I had to squash all commits of a certain branch. I never find my self in any of these scenarios before, so it was quite challenging learning about this. I eventually learned how to squash commits, with some tips from the community and one of my mentors, <a href="https://github.com/Dilu9218">Dilushi</a>. After the second instance of squashing the commits, I was much more comfortable at doing this, for the case where I squashed all the commits of a branch.</p>
<p>Because I was still getting acquainted with flask backend development, I wasn’t doing tests and applying <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test-driven_development">Test-Driven Development (TDD)</a> methodology yet. I was still trying to figure out what was the best way to structure the app to allow me to test each separate module of the app, from DAOs to data model objects and the API itself. So I dedicated a large portion of this week to learn how to test the code. I implemented some basic tests, just to have an idea of how to test the project from now on. Although tests are a very important part of the project development, for now doing all the possible combination of tests wasn’t a priority, this can be done gradually and implemented for the next features. Also, we now have a more stable structure, than in the first weeks, and I understand a bit more of test development for flask applications. Another point is that by having this project open source, anyone can help to add more tests to the project during the GSoC period as well.</p>
<p>I fixed <a href="https://swagger.io/">Swagger</a> documentation of the backend API so that anyone can test the whole API, using the <a href="https://swagger.io/tools/swagger-ui/">Swagger UI</a> instead of just using <a href="https://www.getpostman.com/">Postman</a> (how I usually to test the API). I learned how to use <a href="http://flask-restplus.readthedocs.io">flask-RESTPlus</a> framework to both document header authorization field and request body. The authorization field is required for some endpoints that require login with an access token.</p>
<h3>Shout-outs to blog posts and open source projects</h3>
<p>This week, I discovered other great GitHub open source sample projects that helped me in the learning journey. One of these projects — <a href="https://github.com/mjhea0/flaskr-tdd">mjhea0/flaskr-tdd</a> — shows how to approach TDD using flask applications. Another project that I found was <a href="https://github.com/mjhea0/flask-basic-registration">mjhea0/flask-basic-registration</a>. These two projects were done by <a href="https://github.com/mjhea0">Michael Herman</a>.</p>
<p>I also searched about how to implement email verification for new users, which I’m aiming to start implementing next week. I found <a href="https://realpython.com/handling-email-confirmation-in-flask/">this blog post</a> on this topic, which seems very useful, from <a href="https://realpython.com/">Real Python</a> website. Here’s the <a href="https://github.com/realpython/flask-registration">project from the blog post on GitHub</a>.</p>
<p>Another great article that I found was <a href="https://medium.freecodecamp.org/structuring-a-flask-restplus-web-service-for-production-builds-c2ec676de563">“How to structure a Flask-RESTPlus web service for production builds”</a> by <a href="https://medium.com/@gregobinna">Greg Obinna</a>. I intend to look more into this in the next days. The GitHub project used for this blog post can be found in <a href="https://github.com/cosmic-byte/flask-restplus-boilerplate">cosmic-byte/flask-restplus-boilerplate</a>.</p>
<h3>Plans for next week</h3>
<ul>
<li>Fix bugs found by my mentor and solve small tasks, until thesis presentation;</li>
<li>Implement email verification;</li>
<li>Start implementing features related to users mentorship pairing (probably after thesis presentation);</li>
<li>Create some issues, approved by my mentors, for new contributors to help out. These will be labeled as “first timers only”, which is the Systers label used to guide newcomers into easy quick issues to get started with open source contributions for <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a>.</li>
</ul>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Google Summer of Code | Coding Period | Week 2</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-2/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-2/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-2-cover.png" alt="gsoc plus systers logos"></p>
<p>This week — May 21 to May 27 — was the second week of the coding period of <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code (GSoC)</a> with <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a>. If you want to know more about this you can read the <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc/intro-to-google-summer-of-code-with-systers-open-source-dbdaa92bd189">introduction to my journey</a> or <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc/coding-period-week-1-e8f878f46ad9">my first weekly blog post</a>.</p>
<p>At the beginning of this week I had a 1:1 meeting with one of my mentors, <a href="https://github.com/m-murad">Murad</a>, to clarify some doubts about my code before doing the first pull request with code of at least 4 feature issues and other small features. Since this project is being done from scratch, we need to have a base architecture for the next features to be based on.</p>
<p>The main action items for this week were 2 APIs:</p>
<ul>
<li>One for a User to login into the system;</li>
<li>Another for the User to edit its profile.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Features implemented</h2>
<p>After the 1:1 meeting, I had to fix some endpoints of the API and implement some other features. These were the main features I implemented until now:</p>
<ul>
<li>For security measures, when the user registers (POST /register) to the application, instead of saving the password in plain text, the system saves its hash. I followed the example from <a href="http://flask.pocoo.org/snippets/54/">this snippet from flask website</a> to save the hash and to check it during the authentication and changing the password;</li>
<li>Authentication into the system can be done not only with username + password but with email + password as well. This is mainly done by using <a href="https://pythonhosted.org/Flask-JWT/">flask-JWT</a>, which does all the hard work of generating an access token, and makes a lot easier to identify a specific user by its token;</li>
<li>The first User of the system is automatically an admin, with privileged actions;</li>
<li>An admin can assign another User to be an admin. This is done with this endpoint — POST /admin/new. This endpoint is restricted to authenticated admins;</li>
<li>A User can update its profile, mainly the fields that aren’t filled in the registration phase, such as bio, occupation, location, skills, etc… The endpoint responsible for this is PUT /user, while authenticated;</li>
<li>The User can check its own profile with GET /user, while authenticated;</li>
<li>The User can check others profile with GET /users/{id}, while authenticated;</li>
<li>Verified Users can be seen with GET /users/verified;</li>
<li>A User can change its password with PUT /user/change_password, while authenticated.</li>
</ul>
<p>This <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/pull/14/">Pull Request (PR) comes with all of these first features</a>.
This weekend, I also fixed some <a href="https://www.codacy.com/">Codacy</a> warnings. In case you’re unfamiliar with <a href="https://www.codacy.com/">Codacy</a>, this does automated code reviews regarding code style and other aspects of the code.</p>
<h2>Takeaways</h2>
<p>Aside from implementing these features, I attended the project weekly meeting, GSoC Happy hours and stayed involved with the community apart from GSoC related issues.</p>
<p>These last weeks I started learning a new framework, <a href="http://flask.pocoo.org/">flask</a>, by watching tutorials, reading blog posts, and checking open source sample projects. Comparing to the week before, now I feel much more comfortable with <a href="http://flask-restplus.readthedocs.io">Flask-RESTPlus</a>. This was part of my roadblocks during the coding phase. Although I’m still a beginner at using flask, I’m quicker to implement some feature, now that I have a base architecture and solved some issues while learning the new framework. It’s always challenging to learn a new thing, but it is also rewarding being able to leave the comfort zone and learn how to be a beginner at something again.</p>
<p>One issue I’m still facing is figuring out how to make tests for flask apps, that cover each module of the projects, i.e., resources responsible to serve the endpoints, DAO objects, abstraction with the database and so on. I’m hoping to start doing some mock tests in small steps until I start feeling more comfortable with it.</p>
<p>I have to say that a lot of my work is facilitated due to people open sourcing sample projects and blogging about their experiences. I find this extremely helpful. Here are some open sourced projects that I’ve been looking into with regards to <a href="http://flask-restplus.readthedocs.io">flask-RESTPlus</a>: <a href="https://github.com/postrational/rest_api_demo">postrational/rest_api_demo</a> and <a href="https://github.com/frol/flask-restplus-server-example">frol/flask-restplus-server-example</a>.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Google Summer of Code | Coding Period | Week 1</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-1/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/gsoc-coding-period-week-1/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/gsoc-week-1-cover.png" alt="gsoc and systers logos"></p>
<p>This week — May 14 to May 20 — was the first week of the coding period of <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code (GSoC)</a> with <a href="https://github.com/systers">Systers Open Source</a>. If you want to know more about this you can read the <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc/intro-to-google-summer-of-code-with-systers-open-source-dbdaa92bd189">introduction to my journey here</a>.</p>
<h2>Introduction</h2>
<p>The Coding Period is where the students are dedicated to coding their projects. This period has 3 phases separated by evaluations.
I and the mentors agreed, during a project weekly meeting on the Community Bonding phase, on the action items for the first 4 weeks, which represent the 1º phase of the Coding Period. These action items were then base for my mentors to create the issues so that I could start developing.</p>
<h2>My work items</h2>
<p>After defining the main action items for the 1º phase of the coding period, we distributed them among the 4 weeks. This week I had two action items, for the backend development:</p>
<ul>
<li>API to register a new User in the system;</li>
<li>API to send verification email for new Users.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Roadblocks I had during this week</h2>
<p>First I have to explain some roadblocks I faced this week. Aside from the GSoC program, I’m finishing my Master’s thesis this month. Because of this I still had thesis meetings with my supervisors and I had to start preparing for my Dissertation presentation. This took me some time of the week.
Besides this, I’m not used to developing backend, although this is something I wanted to explore. Since the 1º phase of the coding period requires that I develop a version of the backend with <a href="http://flask.pocoo.org/">flask</a>, I had to study this. I started studying in the Community Bonding period but it wasn’t enough, I still had to experiment in sample projects and watch more video tutorials (provided by one of my mentors), which I did this week. This lack of experience with backend slowed down my initial development. On top of this, I had a problem with my PC, which led me to format the PC, taking me a big portion of an entire day.</p>
<h2>What I did this week</h2>
<p>Having the roadblocks out of the way, I still managed to do some part of my working items. After learning a bit about how to develop using <a href="http://flask-restplus.readthedocs.io">Flask-RESTPlus</a>, I started developing the base architecture of the backend, by implementing the 1º action item — REST API to register users into the mentorship system. I also coded Users <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Create,_read,_update_and_delete">CRUD</a> operations (e.g.: list, update and delete users). I did this already using SQLAlchemy, with the <a href="http://flask-sqlalchemy.pocoo.org">flask-SQLAlchemy</a> extension, which eased a lot of the development. Besides this, I also managed to implement a part of authentication features, with J<a href="https://jwt.io/">SON Web Tokens (JWT)</a>. I did this by using another extension of <a href="http://flask.pocoo.org/">flask</a>, <a href="https://pythonhosted.org/Flask-JWT/">flask-JWT</a>.</p>
<h2>Development and technologies I used</h2>
<p>I’m developing with <a href="https://www.python.org/">Python</a> 3.x and <a href="http://flask.pocoo.org/">flask</a> on my fork of the <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">systers/mentorship-backend</a> repository. You can see the latest version of the code in the <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend/tree/gsoc18-code">gsoc18-code</a> of the main repository.</p>
<p>These are the main extensions of <a href="http://flask.pocoo.org/">flask</a> that I used during this week:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://flask-restplus.readthedocs.io/">Flask-RESTPlus</a> — an extension for flask that facilitates REST APIs development. This also helped exposing <a href="https://swagger.io/">Swagger</a> documentation.</li>
<li><a href="https://pythonhosted.org/Flask-JWT/">Flask-JWT</a> — an extension for flask to add basic <a href="https://jwt.io/">JWT</a> features to a flask. This was used specifically for User authentication with a username and a password, then returning an access-token to login into the System.</li>
<li><a href="http://flask-sqlalchemy.pocoo.org/">Flask-SQLAlchemy </a>— an extension for flask that adds support for <a href="http://www.sqlalchemy.org/">SQLAlchemy</a>. This allowed me to add persistence to the application, in an easy and flexible way.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Setting up the development environment</h2>
<p>I’m developing on <a href="https://www.ubuntu.com/">Ubuntu OS</a>. These are the other tools I’m using for the development:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://virtualenv.pypa.io/">Virtualenv </a>— This allows the creation of isolated Python environments;</li>
<li><a href="https://www.getpostman.com/">Postman </a>— API Development Environment that allows me to test the REST API;</li>
<li><a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/pycharm/">PyCharm </a>— Python Integrated Development Environment (IDE) by JetBrains;</li>
<li><a href="https://atom.io/">Atom </a>— Open source text editor by Github.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Final observations</h2>
<p>I’m a bit late on the actual schedule since I didn’t implement the API to send an email verification yet, and I still have to finish the tests for my code. Nevertheless, I already started implementing some working items from the next weeks, such as Login and Edit profile API. Despite this, I working towards compensating the lost hours with my roadblocks and managing my time wisely.</p>
<p>This week has been a little stressful because of all the roadblocks, I’m very glad that I had my mentors support and understanding. This support really helps me keep calm.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Intro to Google Summer of Code with Systers Open Source</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/intro-gsoc-with-systers-open-source/"/>
    <updated>2018-05-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/intro-gsoc-with-systers-open-source/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/intro-to-gsoc-cover.png" alt="Systers plus Google Summer of Code"></p>
<p>I’m so grateful to be accepted for this year <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code (GSoC)</a> as a student with <a href="http://systers.io/">Systers Open Source community</a>. The results were out April 23rd, and I couldn’t be more excited for this opportunity.</p>
<p>I started engaging with Systers community in the beginning of March. At first it was really intimidating speaking in an open source community, like every message of mine was a broadcast to a crowd of people, but with time I started getting more comfortable to speak out and asking questions. I really like how the community takes the code of conduct very seriously and promotes a welcoming environment for everyone. I already learned a lot from the application phase. One of the things that I learned is that <a href="http://systers.io/newcomers">we can help open source communities with more than code</a>. Soon I’ll share in a blog post the application process.</p>
<p>For this edition of GSoC, I decided to propose a new idea that would benefit the Systers community and that would allow me to explore more of Android development. I proposed <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/projects/#5331289322815488">Systers Mentorship System</a>, an application to match women to help each other. The project goal is to create mentorship relations with a pre-established period of time, in which the mentor volunteers their time to help the mentee in some career growth related topic. This mentorship does not need to be about technical topics, but about those other aspects of a career in tech, such as blogging, public speaking, interviews, etc. I think this can really help new women that are new to the industry, and aren’t sure of how to navigate it.</p>
<p>You can see more details from my <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1TkyLWbVyW9WHEoqFBwpE1GE6vDRf7aoITT6i7tBFKsw/edit#heading=h.dg1yimad8ycj">initial proposal for the idea</a> which has: initial proposed timeline for this summer, the app requirements, an overview of the data model and initial mock screens. Soon I’ll make some posts providing more insights about the proposal for the Mentorship System.</p>
<p>This summer I’ll be developing the back-end and the initial version of the mobile application (Android version), with the guiding of my mentors.</p>
<p>I’ll have two mentors, <a href="https://github.com/Dilu9218">Dilushi Piumwardane</a> and <a href="https://github.com/m-murad">Murad</a> and a project manager, <a href="https://github.com/MayBurgos">Maybellin Burgos</a>.</p>
<p>These project will be completely open source, so anyone can give suggestions and be a part of it. You can join the <a href="http://systers.io/slack-systers-opensource/">Systers Open Source Slack community</a>. Here are the main Github repositories I’ll be working with: <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-backend">systers/mentorship-backend</a> and <a href="https://github.com/systers/mentorship-android">systers/mentorship-android</a>.</p>
<p>I’m very excited for this experience and looking forward to learn from my mentors, the project manager, my fellow <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/organizations/6226384251256832/">GSoC students</a> and open source community.</p>
<p>During the summer I’ll be documenting my journey in <a href="https://medium.com/isabel-costa-gsoc">Isabel Costa GSoC Medium  publication</a>. I already have a few posts in the pipeline ;)</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Signal parent process from child thread using C</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/signal-parent-process-from-child-thread/"/>
    <updated>2018-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/signal-parent-process-from-child-thread/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p>For my master's thesis I had to use signals with C language.</p>
<p>In my code, I used <code>SIGUSR1</code> as the signal I wait for and the <code>handle_my_custom_signal</code> function which will execute once this signal is received in the parent process.</p>
<p>This piece of code allows you to put your program listening for a signal.</p>
<pre><code>signal(SIGUSR1, handle_my_custom_signal);
</code></pre>
<p>This is how I trigger the signal:</p>
<pre><code>raise(SIGUSR1);
</code></pre>
<p><code>SIGINT</code> is used by <em>Ctrl+C</em>. So if you for this signal, your function will be triggered, when you do <em>Ctrl+C</em>.</p>
<p>There are two signals that can be used as we want, without having to waste the <code>SIGINT</code> that is used by <em>Ctrl+C</em>, such as <code>SIGUSR1</code> and <code>SIGUSR2</code>. In <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/libc/manual/html_node/Miscellaneous-Signals.html#Miscellaneous-Signals">this post</a> you can see these and other miscellaneous signals.</p>
<p><a href="https://gist.github.com/isabelcosta/597ef4cc585d44879e6084dec00d166b">This GitHub Gist</a> has the main code of an experiment I did to try this out. You can see the full repository, which contains the <code>Makefile</code> for this: <a href="https://github.com/isabelcosta/testing-signals-with-c">isabelcosta/testing-signals-with-c</a>.</p>
<script src="https://gist.github.com/isabelcosta/597ef4cc585d44879e6084dec00d166b.js"></script>
<p>I actually used this on <a href="https://github.com/inesc-id/Premium">my Master project</a>, more specifically <a href="https://github.com/inesc-id/Premium/blob/71bcf823853869f36ff27b6c1144375e3415c0a4/MACHETE/SCMultipath/sending_handler.c#L394">this line here</a>.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Installing nftables from sources on Debian</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/installing-nftables-from-sources-on-debian/"/>
    <updated>2018-03-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/installing-nftables-from-sources-on-debian/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p>In this post, I’ll show you how I installed <em>nftables</em> from sources. I needed to do this from the sources to have the latest version of <em>nftables</em>.</p>
<p>I needed to work with <a href="https://www.netfilter.org/projects/iptables/index.html">iptables</a> to perform stateless Network Address Translation (NAT) but then I discovered that didn’t appear to be possible by using <em>iptables</em>. So I found <a href="https://netfilter.org/projects/nftables/">nftables</a>, which allows me to do it.</p>
<p>To have the latest version of <em>nftables</em>, at least above v0.7, I installed this tool from the sources. I started by following the instructions on <a href="https://wiki.nftables.org/wiki-nftables/index.php/Building_and_installing_nftables_from_sources">the nftables’ wiki page with the installation instructions</a>.</p>
<p>The <em>nftables</em> package dependencies are listed <a href="https://packages.debian.org/source/stable/nftables">here</a>. These are the main ones:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.netfilter.org/projects/libmnl/">libmnl</a> — the minimalistic Netlink library</li>
<li><a href="https://www.netfilter.org/projects/libnftnl/">libnftnl</a> — low level netlink userspace library</li>
</ul>
<p>First, I tried to install <em>libmnl</em> package provided by on Debian, with <code>aptitude search libmnl</code>, and then I installed <code>libmnl-dev</code>, but it didn’t work for me later, so I installed this from the sources after installing <code>libnftnl</code>.</p>
<hr>
<p>To install <em>libnftnl</em> userspace library, the <em>nftables</em> wiki page suggests these commands:</p>
<pre><code># git clone git://git.netfilter.org/libnftnl
# cd libnftnl
# sh autogen.sh
# ./configure
# make
# make install
</code></pre>
<p>While running the commands, I get the first error (in the third command):</p>
<pre><code>root@debian:/home/debian/libnftnl# sh autogen.sh 
autogen.sh: 3: autogen.sh: autoreconf: not found
</code></pre>
<p>Then I installed the missing packages: <em>autogen</em>, <em>autoreconf</em>.</p>
<pre><code># aptitude install autoconf autogen
</code></pre>
<p>Next, I tried again the <code>sh autogen.sh</code> step and got the following error:</p>
<pre><code>root@debian:/home/debian/libnftnl# sh autogen.sh 
configure.ac:28: error: possibly undefined macro: AC_DISABLE_STATIC
      If this token and others are legitimate, please use m4_pattern_allow.
      See the Autoconf documentation.
autoreconf: /usr/bin/autoconf failed with exit status: 1
</code></pre>
<p>After some research, I found that I had to install <em>libtool</em> package, with <code>aptitude install libtool</code>.</p>
<p>Then I tried again, and  got this output:</p>
<pre><code>root@debian:/home/debian/libnftnl# sh autogen.sh 
libtoolize: putting auxiliary files in AC_CONFIG_AUX_DIR, `build-aux'.
libtoolize: copying file `build-aux/ltmain.sh'
libtoolize: putting macros in AC_CONFIG_MACRO_DIR, `m4'.
libtoolize: copying file `m4/libtool.m4'
libtoolize: copying file `m4/ltoptions.m4'
libtoolize: copying file `m4/ltsugar.m4'
libtoolize: copying file `m4/ltversion.m4'
libtoolize: copying file `m4/lt~obsolete.m4'
configure.ac:8: installing 'build-aux/ar-lib'
configure.ac:8: installing 'build-aux/compile'
configure.ac:5: installing 'build-aux/config.guess'
configure.ac:5: installing 'build-aux/config.sub'
configure.ac:10: installing 'build-aux/install-sh'
configure.ac:10: installing 'build-aux/missing'
examples/Makefile.am: installing 'build-aux/depcomp'
</code></pre>
<p>Finally <code>autogen.sh</code> script is working! In this point, I could move forward to the next command: <code>./configure</code>. Here’s the output I had:</p>
<pre><code>root@debian:/home/debian/libnftnl# ./configure
checking build system type... x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu
checking host system type... x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu
checking for gcc... gcc
checking whether the C compiler works... yes
checking for C compiler default output file name... a.out
checking for suffix of executables... 
checking whether we are cross compiling... no
checking for suffix of object files... o
checking whether we are using the GNU C compiler... yes
checking whether gcc accepts -g... yes
checking for gcc option to accept ISO C89... none needed
checking whether gcc understands -c and -o together... yes
checking for ar... ar
checking the archiver (ar) interface... ar
checking for a BSD-compatible install... /usr/bin/install -c
checking whether build environment is sane... yes
checking for a thread-safe mkdir -p... /bin/mkdir -p
checking for gawk... gawk
checking whether make sets $(MAKE)... yes
checking for style of include used by make... GNU
checking whether make supports nested variables... yes
checking how to create a pax tar archive... gnutar
checking dependency style of gcc... gcc3
checking whether make supports nested variables... (cached) yes
./configure: line 4135: syntax error near unexpected token `LIBMNL,'
./configure: line 4135: `PKG_CHECK_MODULES(LIBMNL, libmnl &gt;= 1.0.0)'
</code></pre>
<p>From this output, I noticed that I was missing the <em>libmnl</em> package, which I installed later, as shown next.</p>
<hr>
<p>To install <em>libmnl</em> userspace library, correctly from the sources, I ran these commands:</p>
<pre><code># git clone git://git.netfilter.org/libmnl
# cd libmnl
# sh autogen.sh
# ./configure
# make
# make install
</code></pre>
<p>With the previous packages I installed, these steps had no errors.</p>
<hr>
<p>Now going back to the installation of <em>libnftnl</em>, I tried to run <code>./configure</code> again and I still got the same problem. I fixed the problem following the instructions of <a href="http://blog.anarey.info/2014/08/pkg_check_moduleslibmnl-libmnl-1-0-0-error/">this blog post</a>. Here are the steps I followed:</p>
<pre><code>root@debian:/home/debian/libnftnl# whereis libmnl
libmnl: /usr/local/lib/libmnl.so /usr/local/lib/libmnl.la /usr/include/libmnl
</code></pre>
<p>Then I did:</p>
<pre><code>root@debian:/home/debian/libnftnl# ldd /usr/local/lib/libmnl.so
 linux-vdso.so.1 (0x00007ffe5212a000)
 libc.so.6 =&gt; /lib/x86_64-linux-gnu/libc.so.6 (0x00007efc29faf000)
 /lib64/ld-linux-x86-64.so.2 (0x000056203c383000)
</code></pre>
<p>The post also suggested that I installed <em>pkg-config</em> with <code>aptitude install pkg-config</code> and install <em>gmp</em> package with <code>aptitude install libgmp3-dev</code>. Here's a post that shows <a href="http://www.mathemagix.org/www/mmdoc/doc/html/external/gmp.en.html">how to install in other Linux distributions here</a>.</p>
<p>Also, the above post suggested that I should configure the pkg-config environment path:</p>
<pre><code># PKG_CONFIG_PATH=/usr/local/lib/pkgconfig
# export PKG_CONFIG_PATH
</code></pre>
<p>Then I ran <code>sh autogen.sh</code> and <code>./configure</code> again. After this I got a much nicer and longer output, like this:</p>
<pre><code>root@debian:/home/debian/libnftnl# ./configure
checking build system type... x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu
checking host system type... x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu
checking for gcc... gcc
checking whether the C compiler works... yes
checking for C compiler default output file name... a.out
checking for suffix of executables... 
checking whether we are cross compiling... no
(...)
checking for LIBMNL... yes
(...)
config.status: creating tests/Makefile
config.status: creating libnftnl.pc
config.status: creating doxygen.cfg
config.status: creating config.h
config.status: executing depfiles commands
config.status: executing libtool commands
libnftnl configuration:
  JSON support:    no
</code></pre>
<p>After this step I finally ran the last two commands  —  <code>make</code> and <code>make install</code>  — 
without any errors.</p>
<hr>
<p>Now that <em>libmnl</em> and <em>libnftnl</em> were successfully installed, I tried to install userspace <em>nft</em> command line utility, <em>nftables</em> from the sources, with the following commands:</p>
<pre><code># git clone git://git.netfilter.org/nftables
# cd nftables
# sh autogen.sh
# ./configure
</code></pre>
<p>While running the last command, <code>./configure</code>, I got an error indicating that I was missing <em>bison</em> package, which the <em>nftables</em> depended on:</p>
<pre><code>root@debian:/home/debian/nftables# ./configure
checking build system type... x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu
checking host system type... x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu
(...)
checking for flex... no
checking for lex... no
checking for bison... no
checking for byacc... no
*** Error: No suitable bison/yacc found. ***
    Please install the 'bison' package.
</code></pre>
<p>Later I got the same message for <em>flex</em> and <em>docbook2x</em> packages. <a href="https://packages.debian.org/source/stable/nftables">Note that both of this are in the <em>nftables</em> dependencies list</a>. So to fix these error messages I installed these packages  —  bison, flex, and docbook2x  —  with <code>aptitude install &lt;package&gt;</code> (e.g.: <code>aptitude install flex</code>).</p>
<p>After this, I got this error message: <code>configure: error: No suitable version of libreadline found</code>. To fix this I followed the <a href="https://www.howtoinstall.co/en/debian/jessie/libreadline-dev">steps of this post</a>.</p>
<pre><code># aptitude update
# aptitude install libreadline-dev
</code></pre>
<p>At this point, I had enough installed to have <em>nft</em> tool running. This is the installation output with no errors:</p>
<pre><code>root@debian:/home/debian/nftables# ./configure
checking build system type... x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu
checking host system type... x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu
(...)
config.status: creating include/linux/netfilter_ipv4/Makefile
config.status: creating include/linux/netfilter_ipv6/Makefile
config.status: creating doc/Makefile
config.status: creating files/Makefile
config.status: creating files/nftables/Makefile
config.status: creating config.h
config.status: executing depfiles commands
config.status: executing libtool commands
nft configuration:
  cli support:                 yes
  enable debugging symbols:    yes
  use mini-gmp:                no
  enable man page:             yes
  enable pdf documentation:    no
  libxtables support:          no
</code></pre>
<p>Then I ran <code>make</code> and <code>make install</code>, also with no errors.</p>
<hr>
<p>Finally, I checked if <em>nftables</em> was successfully installed:</p>
<pre><code>root@debian:/home/debian/nftables# nft
nft: no command specified
root@debian:/home/debian/nftables# nft -v
nftables v0.8.2 (Joe Btfsplk)
</code></pre>
<p>And it was! It worked!</p>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>After all of this procedure, I had to install this on another virtual machine. In this time I tried a simpler approach, with this order:</p>
<ul>
<li>First I ran aptitude update to download lists of new and upgradable packages.</li>
<li>Then I installed all the packages I needed during the first installation, with aptitude install <package-name>. These include <em>autoconf</em>, <em>autogen</em>, <em>libtool</em>, <em>pkg-config</em>, <em>libgmp3-dev</em>, <em>bison</em>, <em>flex</em>, <em>docbook2x</em> and <em>libreadline-dev</em>. You can check the dependencies of <em>nftables</em> <a href="https://packages.debian.org/source/stable/nftables">here</a>.</li>
<li>Next, I configured the path for pkg-config with the following lines:</li>
</ul>
<pre><code># PKG_CONFIG_PATH=/usr/local/lib/pkgconfig
# export PKG_CONFIG_PATH
</code></pre>
<ul>
<li>Then I installed the <a href="https://www.netfilter.org/projects/libmnl/"><em>libmnl</em></a> library, with the commands previously presented:</li>
</ul>
<pre><code># git clone git://git.netfilter.org/libmnl
# cd libmnl
# sh autogen.sh
# ./configure
# make
# make install
</code></pre>
<ul>
<li>After that I installed the <a href="https://www.netfilter.org/projects/libnftnl/"><em>libnftnl</em></a> library, with these commands, also shown previously:</li>
</ul>
<pre><code># git clone git://git.netfilter.org/libnftnl
# cd libnftnl
# sh autogen.sh
# ./configure
# make
# make install
</code></pre>
<ul>
<li>Lastly, I installed <a href="https://www.netfilter.org/projects/nftables/"><em>nftables</em></a> this way:</li>
</ul>
<pre><code># git clone git://git.netfilter.org/nftables
# cd nftables
# sh autogen.sh
# ./configure
# make
# make install
</code></pre>
<ul>
<li>Next, to check if <em>nftables</em> is working, I checked the version with <code>nft -v</code>. Surprisingly I got an error I haven’t seen before, that I fixed with <code>ldconfig</code> command. If you’re unfamiliar with <code>ldconfig</code> you can learn more about it <a href="https://linux.die.net/man/8/ldconfig">here</a>. You can check the sequence of the commands below:</li>
</ul>
<pre><code>root@debian:/home/debian# nft -v
nft: error while loading shared libraries: libnftnl.so.7: cannot open shared object file: No such file or directory
root@debian:/home/debian# ldconfig
root@debian:/home/debian# nft -v
nftables v0.8.2 (Joe Btfsplk)
</code></pre>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>How to upgrade Linux kernel on Debian</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/upgrade-linux-kernel-on-debian/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/upgrade-linux-kernel-on-debian/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p>In this post, I'll show how I updated the virtual machines I worked with. I mostly followed the steps in this great blog post on <a href="https://itsfoss.com/kernel-upgrade-debian/">how to update the kernel in Debian</a>. This post is a short version of that.</p>
<p>I followed the steps in root mode, that's why you won't see <code>sudo</code> here. If you enter in root mode with <code>sudo</code> then add it to the commands.</p>
<p>First, check your Linux kernel version:</p>
<pre><code># uname -r
3.16.0-4-amd64
</code></pre>
<p>Then do a search on the available versions of <code>linux-image</code> and <code>linux-headers</code>, like this:</p>
<pre><code># aptitude search linux-image
v   linux-image               -                                    
v   linux-image-2.6           -                                    
i A linux-image-3.16.0-4-amd6 - Linux 3.16 for 64-bit PCs          
p   linux-image-3.16.0-4-amd6 - Debugging symbols for Linux 3.16.0-
p   linux-image-3.16.0-5-amd6 - Linux 3.16 for 64-bit PCs          
p   linux-image-3.16.0-5-amd6 - Debugging symbols for Linux 3.16.0-
p   linux-image-4.1.38.mptcp  - Linux kernel, version 4.1.38.mptcp 
i A linux-image-4.4.70.mptcp  - Linux kernel, version 4.4.70.mptcp 
p   linux-image-4.4.83.mptcp  - Linux kernel, version 4.4.83.mptcp 
p   linux-image-4.4.83.mptcp- - Linux kernel debugging symbols for 
p   linux-image-4.4.88.mptcp  - Linux kernel, version 4.4.88.mptcp 
p   linux-image-4.9.60.mptcp  - Linux kernel, version 4.9.60.mptcp 
p   linux-image-4.9.78.mptcp  - Linux kernel, version 4.9.78.mptcp 
i   linux-image-amd64         - Linux for 64-bit PCs (meta-package)
p   linux-image-amd64-dbg     - Debugging symbols for Linux amd64 c
</code></pre>
<p>Now to search the headers, do:</p>
<pre><code># aptitude search linux-headers
v   linux-headers             -                                    
v   linux-headers-2.6         -                                    
p   linux-headers-3.16.0-4-al - All header files for Linux 3.16 (me
p   linux-headers-3.16.0-4-al - All header files for Linux 3.16 (me
i   linux-headers-3.16.0-4-am - Header files for Linux 3.16.0-4-amd
i A linux-headers-3.16.0-4-co - Common header files for Linux 3.16.
p   linux-headers-3.16.0-5-al - All header files for Linux 3.16 (me
p   linux-headers-3.16.0-5-al - All header files for Linux 3.16 (me
p   linux-headers-3.16.0-5-am - Header files for Linux 3.16.0-5-amd
p   linux-headers-3.16.0-5-co - Common header files for Linux 3.16.
p   linux-headers-4.1.38.mptc - Linux kernel headers for 4.1.38.mpt
i A linux-headers-4.4.70.mptc - Linux kernel headers for 4.4.70.mpt
p   linux-headers-4.4.83.mptc - Linux kernel headers for 4.4.83.mpt
p   linux-headers-4.4.88.mptc - Linux kernel headers for 4.4.88.mpt
p   linux-headers-4.9.60.mptc - Linux kernel headers for 4.9.60.mpt
i   linux-headers-4.9.78.mptc - Linux kernel headers for 4.9.78.mpt
p   linux-headers-amd64       - Header files for Linux amd64 config
</code></pre>
<p>I shortened the output just to give an idea of the output. Now with this output, you can see the package name for the <code>linux-image</code> and <code>linux-headers</code>. In my case, I want to install the version 4.9.78.mptcp, so I will install like this:</p>
<pre><code># aptitude install linux-image-4.9.78.mptcp linux-headers-4.9.78.mptcp
</code></pre>
<p>After this I restarted the machine, and checked the kernel release with the first command of the post:</p>
<pre><code># uname -r
4.9.78.mptcp
</code></pre>
<p>Yey, a new version of the kernel is installed.</p>
<p>So if this does not work for you, I found <a href="https://itsfoss.com/kernel-upgrade-debian/">this post very helpful</a>.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>How to Undo the Last Commit</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/how-to-undo-the-last-commit/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/how-to-undo-the-last-commit/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*uc89vQwNgfqctnZg9PMfxA.png" alt="Image from Altassian tutorial"></p>
<p>In this post I will show how I sometimes recover wrong changes (commits) in a coding project, using <a href="https://git-scm.com/">git</a> on the command line.</p>
<h3>Why would I want to do this?</h3>
<p>In my thesis, I’m working on a project that I develop in one environment, and then test in another environment composed of multiple virtual machines. So each important change that I do may have a significant impact on the functionalities of the project. Sometimes, the change I do might not have the result I expected. Then I have to see the changes and analyze the project’s behavior before and after the last commit.</p>
<h3>How do you see the last commit?</h3>
<p>To test a specific commit, you need the hash. To get the hash you can run <code>git log</code> , then you get this output:</p>
<pre><code>root@debian:/home/debian/test-project# git log
commit &lt;last commit hash&gt;
Author: Isabel Costa &lt;example@email.com&gt;
Date:   Sun Feb 4 21:57:40 2018 +0000

&lt;commit message&gt;

commit &lt;before last commit hash&gt;
Author: Isabel Costa &lt;example@email.com&gt;
Date:   Sun Feb 4 21:42:26 2018 +0000

&lt;commit message&gt;

(...)
</code></pre>
<p>You can also run <code>git log --oneline</code> to simplify the output:</p>
<pre><code>root@debian:/home/debian/test-project# git log --oneline
&lt;last commit hash&gt; &lt;commit message&gt;
cdb76bf Added another feature
d425161 Added one feature

(...)
</code></pre>
<p>To test a specific commit (e.g.: <code>&lt;before last commit hash&gt;</code>), that you think has the last working version, you can type the following:</p>
<pre><code>git checkout &lt;commit hash&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>This will make the working repository match the state of this exact commit.</p>
<p>After you do this you’ll get the following output:</p>
<pre><code>root@debian:/home/debian/test-project# git checkout &lt;commit hash&gt;
Note: checking out '&lt;commit hash&gt;'.

You are in 'detached HEAD' state. You can look around, make experimental changes and commit them, and you can discard any commits you make in this state without impacting any branches by performing another checkout.

If you want to create a new branch to retain commits you create, you may do so (now or later) by using -b with the checkout command again. Example:

git checkout -b new_branch_name

HEAD is now at &lt;commit hash&gt;... &lt;commit message&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>After analyzing the specific commit, if you then decide to stay in that commit state, you can undo the last commit.</p>
<h3>How to undo this commit?</h3>
<p>If you wish to <a href="https://git-scm.com/docs/git-revert">undo/revert the last commit</a> you can do the following, using the commit hash that you get from the <code>git log</code> command:</p>
<pre><code>git revert &lt;commit hash&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>This command will create a new commit with the “Revert” word in the beginning of the message. After this, if you check your repository status, you’ll notice that you have the HEAD detached at the commit you tested before.</p>
<pre><code>root@debian:/home/debian/test-project# git status
HEAD detached at 69d885e
(...)
</code></pre>
<p><a href="https://www.git-tower.com/learn/git/faq/detached-head-when-checkout-commit">You don’t want to see this message</a>, so to fix this and attach back the HEAD to your working repository, you should checkout the branch you are working on:</p>
<pre><code>git checkout &lt;current branch&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>During the making of this post, I found this tutorial — <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/tutorials/undoing-changes">Undoing Commits and Changes</a> — by Atlassian, which describes this issue very well.</p>
<h3>Summary</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>If you want to test the previous commit just do <code>git checkout &lt;test commit hash&gt;</code> ; then you can test that last working version of your project.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>If you want to revert the last commit just do <code>git revert &lt;unwanted commit hash&gt;</code> ; then you can push this new commit, which undid your previous commit.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>To fix the detached head do <code>git checkout &lt;current branch&gt;</code>.</p>
</li>
</ul>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>My Hack for Good 2017 hackathon experience</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/hack-for-good-2017-experience/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/hack-for-good-2017-experience/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/hackforgood-1.png" alt="My team is in the image, try to find us there (Image from Gulbenkian’s website)"></p>
<p>On the weekend of 24 and 25 of June 2017, I attended <a href="http://hackforgood.pt">Hack for Good</a> hackathon. I’ve already participated in one university hackathon in 2016 and loved it. When I saw there was going to be a hackathon with a mission of coding for social good, I had to assemble a team to participate in this.</p>
<p>This was the 2º edition of Hack For Good. The goal was to create solutions to the problems regarding the refugee’s crisis. Although we knew little about the refugee subject, we still wanted to go. This way, we would gain some technical experience, while contributing to and learning more about an important cause.</p>
<p>After some deliberation, we decided to call our project <a href="https://github.com/CodeFiasco/hack-for-good-2017">REFIND</a>, web platform to host work opportunities for refugees, to bypass prejudice from certain employers.</p>
<h3>The team</h3>
<p>The team had four elements: me, <a href="https://github.com/CodeFiasco">Francisco Machado</a>, <a href="https://github.com/samgomes">Samuel Gomes</a>, and <a href="https://twitter.com/talmeida99">Tiago Almeida</a>. Our name was Penguin. We were highly motivated and wanted to take a chance on this challenge.</p>
<p><em>My team is in the image above :) This image is taken from <a href="https://gulbenkian.pt/project/hack-for-good/">Gulbenkian’s website</a>.</em></p>
<h3>The tools and technology</h3>
<p>Two of us, Me and Tiago, knew about developing mobile applications, more precisely Android. Francisco was more experienced on <a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Ruby on Rails</a>, and I had participated before in a hackathon with him where I learned most of what I know of Ruby on Rails. Samuel had previous experience in data processing/analysis and data visualization, which could help us develop friendly ways to show data about the refugees, and decide which data was relevant for the project.</p>
<p>Regardless of the chosen technology, we were open to learning whatever we thought that worked better?!</p>
<p>Ultimately, we figured that was easier for us to implement a web application using Ruby on Rails since this is a framework easy to learn from both my and Francisco’s experience. Francisco knew the most and was willing to mentor us through the learning process.</p>
<h3>The preparation</h3>
<p>We did two meetings: the first one was a Skype call so that each member got to know each other better and discuss possible ideas; the second meeting was on site to learn and practice the technologies we were going to use.</p>
<p>First, we researched about the refugee’s subject and thought about the project’s model, i.e., how to structure information in the database, and the pages for the web application.</p>
<p>Then, we practiced a bit of Ruby On Rails together with a simple app, where we performed simple operations like Create, Read Update and Delete (CRUD) entities. <a href="https://github.com/isabelcosta/pessoa-app">Here is my application sample.</a></p>
<h3>The idea</h3>
<p>Initially, we wanted to create a tool which helped to reduce the bureaucracy and save time for the people who manage the refugee’s situation from the first day they are welcomed until their inclusion in the new environment. Unfortunately, when we explained such an idea to one of the event’s guests (a former refugee), he told us that our idea lacked “practicability” and adaptability to a real-world scenario.</p>
<p>After that point, we decided to change the idea of the project in the middle of the competition. We then took the time to research a bit more about the subject and then we brainstormed other possible ideas together, while deciding how could we adapt what was already developed.</p>
<p>After some thought, we decided to build REFIND, a web platform to host job offers from unbiased companies towards refugees. Our main goal was to approach the problem of inclusion of refugees in new countries and cultures, and avoid prejudice from companies when hiring refugees.</p>
<p>This next image is the logo we designed during the competition.</p>
<p><img src="/images/hackforgood-2.png" alt="Our project’s logo"></p>
<h3>The environment</h3>
<p>The hackathon was very well organized. It was hosted at the <a href="https://gulbenkian.pt/">Calouste Gulbenkian Foundation</a>. The competition held 33 teams (152 participants) and lasted 36 hours.</p>
<p>They provided all the conditions to allow us to focus on the project. Throughout the event, they provided some workshops, massages and stretch sessions. We had plenty of of food and a lounge where we had games to relax and puffs to sleep if we wanted too.</p>
<p>This next image represents the Hack for Good lounge.</p>
<p><img src="/images/hackforgood-3.png" alt="Hack for Good lounge"></p>
<h3>Development and Organization</h3>
<p>Despite being the team leader, we wore a lot of hats, from developing the codebase, managing issues, and tasks, designing the user interface, deciding the basic features and advanced ones in case we had time. Each member did a bit of everything and had a say in the project decisions.</p>
<h3>After finishing the project</h3>
<p>One of the event mentors, Carolina, taught us a bit about how to sell our idea, how to pitch ourselves to the jury. Therefore we made a short presentation on google slides explaining why our product was suitable to help refugees.</p>
<p>This is a slide from our pitch during the 1º presentation phase, before the top 10 selection.</p>
<p><img src="/images/hackforgood-4.png" alt="Slides (in Portuguese) presented during the 1º presentation phase, before the top 10 selection"></p>
<h3>Things we learned</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>During the event, we were advised of some of the challenges of a project aimed to help refugees. Data security should be one of the main concerns.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Designing user interfaces is very important. People from different countries and backgrounds may perceive interfaces differently. Having accessibility into consideration when designing a product is extremely important.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>It is very important to have a good pitch when presenting an idea. A good pitch can attract potential investors, as it builds a good first impression. We have to be able to explain why our idea is relevant and better than other existing solutions. <a href="https://github.com/CodeFiasco/hack-for-good-2017/blob/master/T21-hack-for-good-presentation.pdf">Here is our presentation in Portuguese</a>.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Outcome</h3>
<p><img src="/images/hackforgood-5.png" alt="Top 10 selected presentations"></p>
<p>We had a lot of fun during the hackathon. The chemistry within the team was great. We lacked some experience compared to some of the competitors, but we were eager to learn and highly motivated to give our best. Although we didn’t get selected to be at the top 10, this experience was totally worth it!</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Inspirational tweets for Blogging</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/inspirational-tweets-for-blogging/"/>
    <updated>2018-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/inspirational-tweets-for-blogging/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/woc-in-tech-chat-2.jpeg" alt="Credits to #WOCinTech Chat photos — wocnintechchat.com"></p>
<p>These are some motivational tweets I saved to motivate me to blog and ease up my insecurities about blogging. Hope this helps other newbies at blogging!</p>
<p>I was inspired to share this because of the <a href="https://2018.codenewbie.org/">#CNC2018</a> Blog More challenge from <a href="https://www.codenewbie.org/">CodeNewbie</a>.</p>
<h4>Una Kravets</h4>
<p>What <a href="https://medium.com/u/a6dfab4de95e">Una Kravets</a> say here really resonates with me because when I took notes at school, I really would come to appreciate it during the phase of exams and tests.</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">A great way to learn a concept is to write a blog post about it<br><br>✍️ Remember taking notes in school?<br><br>It&#39;s like that, but more polished, organized, &amp; filled with links + your own definitions (which helps you think it through)<br><br>Blogging = public notes u can reference &amp; share 😎</p>&mdash; Una Kravets 👩🏻‍💻 (@Una) <a href="https://twitter.com/Una/status/949322814686973952?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 5, 2018</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h4>Craig Russell</h4>
<p>I really needed to see this tweet! At first, I would get really concerned if an idea I had for a post was already out there on the internet. That would really make me give up writing the blog post. Despite my feeling, when I look at this thread I feel much better, because what <a href="https://medium.com/u/e70c655d45e1">Craig Russell</a> says makes sense to me.</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Things I consider before writing a blog post <br><br>✔️ Is this something I find interesting<br>✔️ Is this something I found difficult to learn<br>✔️ Do I want others to know about it<br><br>Things I don&#39;t consider before writing a blog post<br><br>❌ Has someone else already written about it</p>&mdash; Craig Russell (@trionkidnapper) <a href="https://twitter.com/trionkidnapper/status/952498150660505600?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 14, 2018</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>Highlighted sub tweets:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Things I consider before writing a blog post <br><br>✔️ Is this something I find interesting<br>✔️ Is this something I found difficult to learn<br>✔️ Do I want others to know about it<br><br>Things I don&#39;t consider before writing a blog post<br><br>❌ Has someone else already written about it</p>&mdash; Craig Russell (@trionkidnapper) <a href="https://twitter.com/trionkidnapper/status/952498150660505600?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 14, 2018</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">If you have something you want to blog about, do it.<br><br>Don&#39;t hesitate because someone got there first.</p>&mdash; Craig Russell (@trionkidnapper) <a href="https://twitter.com/trionkidnapper/status/952498164300435456?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 14, 2018</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h4>Shubheksha</h4>
<p>This is an awesome thread about the insecurity of having to know everything, and the reach for the perfect blog post, that can cause you to never publish a drafted post. <a href="https://medium.com/u/c98f56800747">Shubheksha</a> gets really candid about this and really helps me to overcome the fear of publishing posts.</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Gentle reminder: you don&#39;t have to know everything about a topic or write a perfect blogpost with no flaws for it to see the light of the day.</p>&mdash; Shubheksha ✨ (@ScribblingOn) <a href="https://twitter.com/ScribblingOn/status/957499377165070336?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 28, 2018</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<p>Highlighted sub tweets:</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I&#39;ve obsessed over this &amp; wasted enough time to realise that it&#39;s harming me in more than one way. <br><br>What I gain from writing that post is far more valuable than my irrational fear of missing or presenting something incorrectly.</p>&mdash; Shubheksha ✨ (@ScribblingOn) <a href="https://twitter.com/ScribblingOn/status/957500230655664128?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 28, 2018</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I think I learnt a lot of this by seeing how <a href="https://twitter.com/b0rk?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@b0rk</a> blogs. She writes about what she&#39;s currently learning, mentions when she&#39;s not sure of something, is happy to be corrected &amp; open to having gaps filled in by other ppl.</p>&mdash; Shubheksha ✨ (@ScribblingOn) <a href="https://twitter.com/ScribblingOn/status/957506676969562112?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 28, 2018</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<h4>Christina Lee</h4>
<p>This one reminds me that you can learn a lot from blogging, the research for the blog post topic, and the willingness to have a good blog post makes you learn more about the topic. As <a href="https://medium.com/u/72bd5082d8aa">Christina Lee</a> says, this also applies for public speaking.</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">A pretty good description of how public speaking and writing can make you a better developer. I love the term &quot;knowledge transforming&quot; to describe this sort of process. <br><br>Excerpt from Peak, by Anders Ericsson and Robert Pool <a href="https://t.co/XjfTK407e1">pic.twitter.com/XjfTK407e1</a></p>&mdash; Christina Lee (@RunChristinaRun) <a href="https://twitter.com/RunChristinaRun/status/958015646192644096?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 29, 2018</a></blockquote> <script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
<hr>
<p>For now this are the tweets that I saved regarding blogging motivation. If I see others that might help, I’ll add here.</p>
<p>Share this with anyone that might be one motivational tweet away of starting or blog more.</p>
<p><em>The picture in this post is from the awesome initiative <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/wocintechchat/">#WOCinTech Chat photos</a> — <a href="http://wocnintechchat.com">wocnintechchat.com</a></em></p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Tools I use for my Master’s thesis</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/tools-i-use-for-my-masters-thesis/"/>
    <updated>2018-01-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/tools-i-use-for-my-masters-thesis/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/thesis-onenote-tool.png" alt="Example of my organization on OneNote"></p>
<p>During Master’s thesis, I use a lot of tools to organize my thoughts, relevant information and resources related to my research. These do not include tools that I use for development/coding, it is only refers to things related with writing of the Dissertation and notes I take.</p>
<h3>OneNote</h3>
<p><a href="https://www.onenote.com/">OneNote</a> is the main tool I use to write all my thoughts related to my thesis, and what is discussed at the meetings with my supervisors. I use the Windows app, because of its simplicity and the few features it has. It opens very quickly on my computer. I use a section for the thesis and then I organize all information (e.g.: notes from the meetings) in pages and subpages for each meeting with my supervisors, and other related stuff.</p>
<h3>TeXstudio</h3>
<p>I use <a href="https://www.latex-project.org/">LaTeX</a> to write my thesis. <a href="https://www.texstudio.org/">TeXstudio</a> is the tool I use to write the document offline. The implementation of latex that I use is <a href="https://miktex.org/">MiKTeX</a>, which I needed to work on TeXstudio. There are other tools useful to write LaTeX documents, which work online and allow real-time collaboration, such as, <a href="https://www.overleaf.com/">Overleaf</a> and <a href="https://www.sharelatex.com/">ShareLatex</a>. When I have to work on a smaller document and need to collaborate in real-time, I tend to use Overleaf.</p>
<h3>Mendeley</h3>
<p>I use <a href="https://www.mendeley.com/">Mendeley</a> to save all papers related to the thesis. I love this tool because I can easily browse specific keywords on all the papers. I also highlight all the important parts from the papers, so that I can review later. As a side note if you’re beginning a Dissertation and want to search for papers, these sites may help you finding them: <a href="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/">IEEE Xplore Digital Library</a>; <a href="https://scholar.google.com/">Google Scholar</a>; <a href="https://dl.acm.org/">ACM Digital Library</a>.</p>
<h3>Dropbox</h3>
<p>I use <a href="https://www.dropbox.com/">Dropbox</a> to share all the versions of the dissertation and project documents. So that my supervisors can track my progress and review my work. I also use <a href="https://www.google.com/drive/">Google Drive</a> to save illustrations, which I create with the next tool, or <a href="https://www.google.com/docs/about/">Google Docs</a> documents that may be shared with others.</p>
<h3>Draw.io</h3>
<p>I use <a href="https://www.draw.io/">Draw.io</a> to build diagrams and illustrations to better explain ideas and concepts. I feel this is very easy to use and allows me to create simple diagrams very quickly. I save these diagrams on my <a href="https://www.google.com/drive/">Google Drive</a>.</p>
<h3>Github</h3>
<p>I use <a href="https://github.com/">Github</a> Wiki and Issues features to track my research and document what I learn on topics and projects related to the thesis. This is shared with my supervisors so they can easily access it and give feedback.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
  
  <entry>
    <title>Overcoming shyness at my first meetup alone</title>
    <link href="https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/overcoming-shyness-at-my-first-meetup-alone/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://isabelcosta.github.io//posts/overcoming-shyness-at-my-first-meetup-alone/</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
      <p><img src="/images/shy-dog.jpeg" alt=""></p>
<p>A few days ago I went to a meetup about women in tech, organized by <a href="https://www.small-improvements.com/">Small Improvements</a>, in the week of WebSummit. The objective was to get as many points of view as possible on why there are few women in tech and discuss possible solutions to overcome it.</p>
<p>So I’m an extremely shy person, I tend to go to a few meetups but I always go with someone. I do this so I can always talk with someone, in case I cannot start or include myself in a conversation.</p>
<p>This time I went alone. When I committed to go I wanted to push myself and not let my social anxiety win. However, that day wasn’t going very well so I had a lot of doubts of going. In the end I just went for it, I thought about what was the worst thing that could happen: I would be in a crowd of people completely silent… No one would talk to me… Or they would talk and I would somehow make a fool out of myself… And many other fears. But my desire of trying to overcome fear of embarrassment and feeling lonely was greater than my fears.</p>
<h3>The outcome</h3>
<p>The event went pretty well :) It was a great experience, one that I would not have imagined. It was a small group of people, both men and women, where everyone had a voice. All opinions were heard. People were truly concerned about the topic, and wanted to know each other’s opinion. It wasn’t a debate where some people were debating and the audience would have a public Q&amp;A at the end. Therefore it was a perfect environment for me, being a small group of people where I would feel more comfortable about speaking up, and people were as interested in my point of view as they were for anyone at the table.</p>
<p>All of the them were really kind and down to earth.</p>
<h3>Conclusion</h3>
<p>It was a great experience that I would have missed if I avoided the event because of my shyness. These were some of the benefits:</p>
<ul>
<li>I got to meet new and great people</li>
<li>I got to share my point of view on women in tech</li>
<li>I got a chance to practice my English (since I’m not a native english speaker)</li>
<li>I’m one step closer to feeling comfortable in social situations</li>
</ul>
<p>So even though this went very well, that doesn’t mean that all of the next meetups will be as great as this one. However, sometimes we have to take chances, and this one I took was definitely worth it!</p>
<p>Finally, I really hope that my experience can show to other shy and anxious people that they can also do this, with good hopes of having a good experience.</p>
<p>So share this with anyone you might feel that would benefit from my experience.</p>

    ]]></content>
  </entry>
	
</feed>
